<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
 RcnR, resistance to cobalt and nickel regulator protein is an addition to  set of transcriptional metallo-regulator proteins of E. coli (some of  main ones are Fur, CueR, CusR, MntR, Zur, ZntR, and NikR) [16956381] that regulate  transcriptional expression of a recently described efflux protein, RcnA [15805538] to maintain <RP>nickel and cobalt homeostasis </RP>[16956381, 17120142].  homeostasis of different metals in  cell is constantly monitored, and adequate pathways are activated or repressed to keep  metals within normal levels. Specifically, when nickel and cobalt exceed  normal levels, cell growth stops [16956381]. 
 rcnR gene is encoded divergently to  rcnA gene, which encodes an efflux protein that is involved in nickel and cobalt homeostasis [15805538] it removes an excess of ions [16956381]. It has been proved by Koch and colleagues [17120142]that  <TUR>rcnR gene is  target of Fur regulation in regard to iron levels</TUR> (when iron increases, rcnR expression increases about 2.3-fold [17120142]. 
<DOM>An RcnR structure study showed that it has a charged N-terminal region (amino acids 1-34), followed by a highly conserved region of primarily nonpolar amino acids (35-64), that is, probably involved in binding metals.  N terminus determines metal-specific responses in  recognition of cognate and noncognate metals [22471551]. Its secondary structure prediction shows three helices without any β-sheet [16956381]. </DOM>
RcnR is not similar to any or known transcriptional regulator; instead, it is homologous to or proteins whose genes are encoded next to genes encoding putative metal efflux proteins, metalloenzymes, or copper chaperones [and just <EVPIT>a few (13%) of  homologs to cardiolipin synthases or membrane proteins</EVPIT>] [16956381]. Such conserved localization with genes of metal-related functions suggests that se homologs are likely to play a regulatory role in metal homeostasis [16956381]. 
RcnR acts as a transcriptional repressor for its divergent rcnA gene [16956381]and a weak repressor for its own expression [19703465]. <ACTCONDN>In response to increasing concentrations of nickel or cobalt, RcnR releases  repression of rcnA and rcnR to allow its expression</ACTCONDN> [16956381, 19703465]. As <TUCREG>rcnR expression is induced in response to iron even in  absence of Fur</TUCREG> [17120142] it is possible that RcnR responds to iron ions directly. 
RcnR binds to <SSA>two sites in  rcnA-rcnR  intergenic region with  sequence TACT-G(6)-N-AGTA</SSA> [19703465, 16956381].  TACT <SSM>inverted repeats</SSM> are critical for specific binding.  G-tracts provide a structural component to facilitate binding of RcnR to DNA, because y endow A-form DNA characteristics to  RcnR operators. In addition, RcnR interacts nonspecifically with  approximately 50 bp flanking  core binding site, resulting in DNA wrapping and  introduction of a single negative supercoil into plasmid DNA [19703465]. RcnR forms a stable tetramer and binds as a tetramer to one operator.  tetrameric state is not perturbed by Ni(II) or Co(II) binding [18505253]. 
As nickel levels depend on  Nik uptake system (NikR regulator, NikABCDE transporter) and nickel is highly used during anaerobic growth by  Ni-Fe hydrogenase isozyme,  additional participation of RcnR and RcnA in nickel homeostasis changes  previous understanding of  cell's nickel processing. Iwig and colleagues [16956381]showed that RcnR is not directly related to or proteins that use nickel, although y showed that RcnA, as  exporter of excess ions, has direct participation. RcnA likely competes with NikR for nickel ions at low concentrations, and in such a way RcnA downregulates nikABCDE expression and nickel uptake (for this, rcnA must be expressed at a basal level prior to induction, as observed with higher nickel levels) [16956381]. Also, RcnA is important in  modulation of  hydrogenase assembly pathway through  NikR regulation that limits nickel delivery to  process, repressing nikABCDE transporter expression when intracellular nickel levels are high [16956381].
Reviews: [22970729].
</SUMMARY>