<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
biotin repressor,  BirA, coordinately represses transcription of  divergent genes that are necessary for <RP> synsis of biotin</RP> [6177001, 366433]. BirA is a bifunctional protein that possesses both regulatory and enzymatic activities: it acts as  DNA-binding transcriptional repressor of  biotin operon and also exhibits <RP>biotin ligase activity</RP> [6129246].
<ACTEFFE> specific inducer for BirA is  biotinyl-5'-adenylate (bio-5'-AMP)</ACTEFFE>. <ACTCONDP>In  presence of bio-5'-AMP, <SSA>BirA binds to <SSZ>40-nucleotide-long</SSZ> DNA target sites in  bioA/bioBFCD intergenic region</SSA></ACTCONDP>  to coordinately repress transcription of bioAp and bioBp [9485476, 1659455]. BirA-bio-5'-AMP has been observed to be predominantly monomeric in solution [6129246, 8373769, 9485476] whereas more recent studies indicate that dimerization occurs before DNA binding [12527300]. Biotinyl-5'-adenylate [10529178]and biotin [11353844, 350835]stimulate dimerization and DNA binding. 
<ACTEFFE> effector bio-5'-AMP</ACTEFFE> is also a substrate in  BirA-mediated biotinylation of  biotin carboxyl carrier protein monomer (apoBCCP), and this relationship results in repression of  biotin operon when  abundance of apoBCCP (and refore  cellular demand for biotin) is reduced [9750231]. <ACTREG>This repression is controlled by  rate of  competing protein:protein interaction</ACTREG>.  rate of heterodimerization with apoBCCP controls  holoBirA monomer supply, and  equilibrium constant of homodimerization tunes  bioO occupancy and, consequently, transcription initiation at  biotin operon [23896299].
 crystal structure of BirA has been determined by X-ray crystallography to a resolution of 2.3 Å [1409631] and that of a BirA-biotin complex [11353844]has been solved by several research groups. Crystallization has been described [2642476] and  implications of  structure with respect to  binding of biotin and ATP have been discussed [1409631].  
<DOM> BirA monomer contains three domains: an amino-terminal domain that contains a helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motif;  central domain, which is important for DNA binding and catalysis and contains  binding site for bio-5'-AMP; and  C-terminal domain,  funtion of which has yet to be determinded. Disordered loop structures on  protein surface appear to be involved in binding to biotin, bio-5'-AMP, and/or DNA [10497026] and in protein dimerization [11353844].</DOM> A model of binding and reaction progression is presented elsewhere [11847279].
</SUMMARY>