<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Catabolite repressor activator,  Cra, which was initially named  Fructose repressor,   FruR,  is a dual transcriptional regulator that plays a <RP>pleiotropic role to modulate  direction of carbon flow through  different metabolic pathways of energy metabolism, but independently of  CRP regulator [9084760, 8577250, 8230205, 18648770]. For this reason  FruR regulator is implicated in  expression of a large number of operons that encode enzymes which comprise central pathways of carbon metabolism. 
FruR acts as an activator of genes encoding gluconeogenic [8550429, 8577250, 2496106, 9084760, 3542978] Krebs cycle [16415587, 9084760] and glyoxylate shunt [8195118, 16415587, 9084760] enzymes, and  negative effect on genes encoding Entner-Doudoroff pathway [9084760, 18648770]and glycolytic enzymes</RP> [8550429, 8577250, 9084760]. 
Cra carries out a glycolytic flux-dependent regulation. <ACTREG> glycolytic flux is determined by  concentration of  <ACTEFFE>metabolite fructose-1,6-bisphosphate, which is  molecular effector of Cra</ACTEFFE></ACTREG> [23277571].
FruR forms a complex with DNA in  absence of fructose 1-phosphate or fructose 1,6-phosphate, <SSA>binding to an <SSZ>18-bp-long sequence</SSZ> with an <SSM>imperfect palindromic sequence</SSM></SSA> [9084760, 16115199, 8195118, 8577250, 8858581]. <ACTREG>In  presence of glucose it increases  intracellular concentration of  metabolites d-fructose 1-phosphate and d-fructose 1,6-phosphate</ACTREG>, which interact with FruR to prevent its binding or displacement of  target operons [8230205, 8577250, 8550429]. <ACTREG>FruR is inactivated upon  interaction of  inducers</ACTREG>. FruR has been observed to be predominantly a tetrameric structure in solution [8195118].
FruR <EVF>belongs to  GalR-LacI family of transcriptional regulators</EVF>, which are helix-turn-helix DNA-binding proteins [1805309, 1639817, 2198273]. As a member of this family <DOM>FruR contains two functional domains: an N-terminal domain which contains a helix-turn-helix motif for DNA binding, and  effector binding domain located in  C terminus, which is homologous to  periplasmic  sugar-binding protein for ribose, arabinose, and galactose.</DOM>
deletion of  fruR gene causes a reduction in cellular growth. This effect could be due to  inhibition of  osmoprotectant producing  genes, betA, betB, and betT [21718532].
</SUMMARY>