<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
CreB  Carbon source responsive response regulator,  is a DNA-binding transcriptional dual regulator [11350954, 18375564]and belongs to  CreBC two-component system (TCS) [2228961, 11350954, 18375564] which controls genes involved in <RP>acetate [7883769]and ribose [10542272]metabolism, in  maltose regulon [9000616] in  pentose phosphate pathway [8572885] and genes which repair DNA damage associated with  replication fork</RP> [10224240]. 
CreBC regulates  expression of cre regulon genes in response to a switch from complex to minimal medium [11350954]. <ACTCONDP>It is active when cells are fermenting glycolytic carbon sources</ACTCONDP>. Induction of  cre regulon during pyruvate growth is entirely CreC dependent [18375564].
CreBC is considered a global regulator that is positioned at  heart of metabolic control [11350954].
<TUL>CreB and CreC are part of  creABCD operon</TUL> [18375564]. CreB binds in vitro to a <SSA>TTCACnnnnnnTTCAC sequence called  cre tag <SSM>direct repeat</SSM></SSA>, which stimulates  cre regulon [18375564].
<EVPIT>CreBC (TCS) is homologous (60-70%) with BrlAB of Aeromonas spp.</EVPIT> at  amino acid level [11350954].
CreC can act as   phosphate donor for PhoB in PhoR mutants ([11350954]and references rein) but this activity is masked in PhoR+ strains and  CreC/PhoB pathway is not responsive to phosphate levels [7021308].  
A model of regulation by CreBC was proposed by Cariss et al. (2008) in which <ACTREG>CreC responds to changes in  growth medium and/or signal and autophosphorylates; later, its phosphate is passed on to CreB</ACTREG>, which binds to cre tag sequences. CreB functions as a transcriptional activator by recruiting RNA polymerase, whereas  binding of CreB to  cre tag represses transcription through promoter occlusion [18375564].
<ACTREG> antimicrobial peptide lactoferricin B, binds to CreB and inhibits its phosphorylation in vitro</ACTREG> [22138548]. 
</SUMMARY>