<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Rhamnose regulator,  RhaS, is a transcription factor involved in <RP>l-rhamnose degradation and transport</RP> [8230210, 7966303, 8757746]. RhaS alone is able to activate transcription of rha operons, but in  presence of CRP, transcription increases. On  or hand, CRP alone is unable to activate transcription of rha operons in  absence of RhaS. refore, se two regulators bind cooperatively to fully activate  operons related with transport and degradation of l-rhamnose [16166533, 8230210, 8757746, 10852886]. Additionally, <TUCREG>synsis of rha operons is induced when E. coli is grown on l-rhamnose in  absence of glucose and when cellular cyclic AMP levels are high</TUCREG> [16166533].
RhaS is <TUL>part of  unusual rhaSR operon</TUL> that encodes two transcriptional regulators, <EVPIT>RhaS and RhaR (30% identical)</EVPIT>, both <EVF>members of  AraC/XylS family of transcriptional regulators</EVF> [10464186, 17071764]. Apparently, expression of operons involved in transport and degradation of l-rhamnose first requires expression of RhaR, which induces transcription of  rhaSR operon. In this way, RhaS activates transcription of l-rhamnose gene clusters.
<DOM>This transcription factor is composed of two domains, a C-terminal domain that contains two potential helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motifs and an N-terminal domain involved in l-rhamnose binding and dimerization of  protein [15342598, 18366439, 17513476]. Mutational studies carried out to define interactions between RhaS and σ70 suggest  existence of two interaction regions in both.  contact regions through which both proteins interact are represented by two amino acid residues in  C-terminal domains of RhaS (D241 and D250) and σ70 (R599 and K593) [10940041, 15342598].</DOM>
<ACTCONDP>In  presence of l-rhamnose, RhaS binds in tandem to repeat sequences upstream of  rhaAp and rhaTp intergenic regions</ACTCONDP>.  binding site for RhaS overlaps  -35 region of both rhaBp and rhaTp promoters in 4 bp. <SSA> binding targets for RhaS consist of <SSZ>17-nucleotide-long sequences</SSZ> that possess conserved motifs</SSA>; each monomer binds to one of se conserved sequences [15342598, 10852886]. It seems  binding sites of RhaS are on a different face of  DNA relative to  rhaBAD operon [7966303, 17513476].
</SUMMARY>