<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
regulatory protein for  uptake of hexose phosphates,  UhpA [4902320] activates  transcription of a gene that codes for <RP>UhpT, a protein that transports many phosphorylated sugars into  cell </RP>[6309737].
UhpA is  response regulator in  unusual two-component regulatory system comprised of three proteins, UhpA/UhpB/UhpC, and is a <EVF>member of  NarL subfamily of response regulators</EVF>.  signal that triggers this signaling pathway is glucose 6-phosphate external. This sugar is sensed by UhpC, which interacts with UhpB to stimulate its autophosphorylation. n, phosphorylated <DOM><ACTREG>UhpB transfers  phosphate group to UhpA in Asp-54 to activate it</ACTREG> [11739766]. UhpB unphosphorylated is able to dephosphorylate to UhpA [11325944, 11739766].
UhpA has two modules:  receiver module, which contains  putative site of phosphorylation in  N-terminal domain [7596290] and  activation module, which contains a helix-turn-helix motif for DNA binding in  C-terminal domain[7596290, 3042748].</DOM> <EVPIT>UhpA shows 30% identity with DctD</EVPIT> [3042748].
RNA polymerase RpoA and RpoD subunits are necessary for  transcriptional activation by UhpA[10572130] which induces open complex formation, but <ACTCONDP> stabilization of this complex is CRP dependent</ACTCONDP> [10512697]. se two regulatory proteins appear to stimulate  DNA binding of each or to  uhpT promoter [10512697].
Two UhpA dimers bind to two sites with different affinities upstream of uhpT.  weak site is essential for activation, and its occupancy is dependent on  occupancy of  strong site. <SSA>This site contains <SSM>inverted repeats</SSM> with  consensus CCTGA/GA/G separated by 6 bp</SSA> [11976297].
<TUL><TURO> uhpT, uhpC, uhpB, and uhpA genes are located in tandem</TURO> in  same locus in  genome</TUL>, and while uhpT is transcribed alone [1569008] it has been demonstrated that uhpB and uhpA are transcribed in  same operon and re is  possibility that uhpC is transcribed with m [3038843].
</SUMMARY>