<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Cu efflux regulator , CueR, regulates genes related to <RP> primary copper homeostasis system </RP>[15773991, 11167016, 11222619, 10915804]<ACTCONDP>in response to  presence of copper, silver, or gold ions</ACTCONDP> [15773991, 12832075, 12446701].
crystal structures of CueR dimers bound to Cu+, Ag+, or Au+ have been solved [12958362]. <DOM>Each monomer consists of three domains, an N-terminal DNA-binding domain carrying two helix-turn-helix motifs, a central dimerization domain, and a C-terminal metal-binding domain.  DNA-binding and dimerization domains are <EVF>characteristic of  MerR family of proteins</EVF>.  dimerization domain contains a 10-turn α-helix that forms an antiparallel coiled-coil with  helix of  or monomer.  metal-binding domain contains an unusual metal receptor site in which  bound metal is inaccessible to  solvent.  metal ion is bound with a linear coordination to two conserved cysteine residues. </DOM>This dithiolate coordination confers  metal ion selectivity for +1 ions [12958362].  sensitivity of CueR for copper(I) ions is extremely high (in  zeptomolar range), which corresponds to less than one atom per cell. Apparently it is  task of CueR and CopA to clear  toxic copper ions rapidly from  cytoplasm into  periplasmic space [12958362].
CueR activates transcription by overlapping  -35 box of promoters and represses it by binding downstream of  transcription start site [11136469]. CueR  binds to <SSA>a <SSZ>19-bp sequence</SSZ> containing two 7-bp <SSM>inverted repeats</SSM> separated by a 7-bp spacer</SSA> [11136469].  Binding occurs in vitro in both  presence and  absence of copper ions. Holo-CueR binds more strongly to DNA than apo-CueR and with a higher conformational flexibility [19651042] Both holo- and apo-CueR bend DNA [19651042].  formation of permanganate-sensitive transcription complexes requires copper ions [11136469].
Reviews: [12829268, 16158235, 12829265, 22918892].
</SUMMARY>