<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
arabinose regulator,  AraC, is a transcription factor that regulates transcription of several genes and operons involved in <RP>arabinose catabolism and transport</RP>. It coregulates with anor transcriptional regulator, CRP; both are transcription factors involved in l-arabinose degradation. se regulators bind cooperatively to activate transcription of five operons related to transport, catabolism, and autoregulation of l-arabinose. Transcription of se operons is induced when E. coli is grown in  absence of glucose and when  physiological inducer, <ACTEFFE>l-arabinose</ACTEFFE>, binds to  AraC regulator. <ACTCONDP>In  absence of glucose, cellular cyclic AMP levels are high and cyclic AMP forms a dimeric complex with CRP to coregulate with AraC</ACTCONDP> [9409145, 1744033, 6319708, 1400237, 9600836, 2231717, 6377308]. 
AraC binds to five target sites in  araBp region. <ACTCONDP>AraC binds to  less-conserved site (-42.5) with less strength; this binding occurs only in  presence of arabinose</ACTCONDP>, and it is absolutely required for expression of araBp [2237403, 3279415, 2962192, 3520549, 8428590]. AraC binding to  distal site (-123.5) has been shown to down-regulate expression of araBp and araCp [1560456, 3279415]. 
In  absence of arabinose, AraC is unable to activate araBp, but <TUR>it regulates its own expression by repressing araCp and araBp simultaneously</TUR> [2237403, 3279415, 3520549]. Arabinose triggers AraC-dependent activation of araBp and relieves AraC-dependent repression of araCp [3279415, 3520549]. <TUL> araBAD operon is located upstream of araC and in  opposite direction.</TUL>
<ACTCONDP>In  presence of arabinose, this regulator activates transcription by overlapping  -35 box of  core promoters</ACTCONDP>, and  central position of  binding site is located near bp -41.5. <SSA> binding targets for AraC consist of <SSZ>17-nucleotide-long</SSZ> <SSM>direct repeat sequences</SSM> that possess conserved motifs</SSA>; each monomer binds to one of se conserved sequences [9409145, 8980677]. 
AraC regulator <EVF>belongs to  AraC/XylS family</EVF> and occurs as both a monomer and a homodimer. <DOM>It is composed of two domains.  solution structure of  C-terminal DNA-binding domain has been solved. It consists of two helix-turn-helix regions connected by an α-helix [19422057].  N-terminal domain is responsible for dimerization and L-arabinose binding [9409145, 8451183]. Its crystal structure [9367758, 9103202] reveals that  sugar molecule is bound within a β-barrel, buried by  N-terminal arm of  protein. It has been suggested that this N-terminal arm plays a key role in  regulation of  arabinose-dependent DNA-binding properties of  protein. <ACTREG>In  absence of arabinose it interacts with  DNA-binding domain and constrains this domain, and it releases it in  presence of arabinose</ACTREG> [9103202, 18561170, 19815018]. This interaction appears to be affected by a mutation in  interdomain linker [21840981]. Mutations at position 15 in  N-terminal arm of AraC do not activate transcription in  presence of arabinose, and this was confirmed by using a molecular dynamic (MD) simulation, which revealed that preservation of  shape of  arm is critical to inducibility [23150197].</DOM>
A negative autoregulation network motif increases  input dynamic range of  arabinose system by coupling  transcription factor protein level to  input signal [21749723].
</SUMMARY>