<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
TrpR,  tryptophan ARRAY(0x15bd560) transcriptional repressor,  negatively regulates expression of  trp regulon in response to intracellular levels of tryptophan [7012834].  TrpR regulon is involved in <RP>tryptophan biosynsis, transport, and regulation</RP>. This regulon partially overlaps with  TyrR regulon, since expression of several genes is regulated by TrpR and TyrR,  transcriptional regulator of  TyrR regulon [7961453, 1904443, 2061290].
TrpR represses transcription by interfering with  ability of RNA polymerase to interact with  promoter [1097702].  aporepressor <ACTREG>is activated as a DNA-binding protein by noncooperative binding of <ACTEFFE>two L-tryptophan molecules</ACTEFFE> to  homodimer</ACTREG> [1097702, 3519217, 3549712]. <SSA> consensus sequence for TrpR is described as two symmetrically arranged half-sites with  sequence GNACT separated by a spacer of 8 bp</SSA> [8613990].
X-ray crystallography of  aporepressor [3600756]  holorepressor [3903514] and repressor bound to  operator oligonucleotide [3419502] as well as NMR studies of  repressor and aporepressor in solution [8433368] and bound to an operator oligonucleotide [7957174] reveal that  small 25-kDa protein <EVF>belongs to  helix-turn-helix (HTH) family</EVF>.  dimer is composed of two identical six-helical subunits, where four of  helices intertwine with  corresponding helices from  or subunit.<DOM> Binding of tryptophan stabilizes  HTH and alters  orientation of  HTH such that  repressor fits into  major grooves [3600756].</DOM>
crystal structure of  repressor-operator complex reveals that specific binding is mostly mediated by contacts to  phosphate backbone and water-mediated hydrogen bonds, suggesting that  intrinsic DNA structure rar than  specific base pairs are recognized, a mechanism which has been termed indirect readout [3419502].
</SUMMARY>