<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
HU protein is a small DNA-binding protein that is considered a global regulatory protein and shares properties with histones, which play an important role in nucleoid organization [10515926, 10551881, 10947847, 19245936] and regulation [16258062, 11254141, 19194530, 9218807, 15289461, 9192630]. 
HU is a heterodimer formed by an α-subunit and a β-subunit, which are encoded by  hupA and hupB genes, respectively [3312963, 3069589, 6987059, 2187099, 2001682] and are differentially stimulated during cold shock [11967080]. HU is a transcriptional dual regulator. HU-1 (HupB) and HU-2 (HupA) are closely related but differ by 28 residues, and y have a high content of hydrophobic residues represented mostly by alanine. re is no sequence homology between  proteins HU-1 and HU-2 compared to any of  five histones of different eukaryotes studied [6987059]. 
HU forms  high-affinity complexes with DNA containing sharp bends, kinks, branched and bulged structures, or single-strand breaks and loops [8089835, 7730334, 8646783, 9016640, 8459763].
Three dimeric forms exist in Escherichia coli: two homodimers, EcHUα2  and EcHUβ2, and a heterodimer, HUαβ [12875839]. All se forms are in rmal equilibrium between two dimeric conformations (N2@@lt@@--@@gt@@I2) that vary in ir secondary structure content [20936276].
Based on high-temperature molecular dynamics simulation and NMR experiments, information has been obtained about  structural and dynamic features at  atomic level for  N2@@lt@@--@@gt@@I2 rmal transition of  EcHUβ2 homodimer [20936276]. A 3D model has been proposed for  major I2 conformation of EcHUβ2 [20936276].
 crystal structure of  DNA-HUαβ complex has been resolved [17360520]. In  presence of poly(P), HupA is efficiently degraded by Lon [17543195].  presence of HU depends on  phase of growth [10515926] and it is distributed uniformly in  nucleoid [10947847]. Currently, <ACTEFFE>no inducer for this regulator has been reported in  literature</ACTEFFE>. 
HU <EVF>belongs to a family of DNA architectural proteins</EVF> and acts mostly as a regulatory or accessory factor, stabilizing a correct nucleoprotein complex [12372591, 17259223, 1925023]. For example, <ACTCONDP>HU introduces negative supercoiling in covalently closed circular DNA in  presence of topoisomerase I</ACTCONDP> [222478, 1579448].  HU protein has been shown to be involved in DNA replication [9171392, 12366835, 1879696] and  formation of transcription foci [20010798] and it modulates  binding of IHF to oriC [1425583] and stabilizes  DnaA oligomer bound to oriC [18179598]. As anor example, HU is required for  expression of σS factors [11251825]. Recently, Oberto et al. showed that HU also plays an important role in  regulation of many genes in response to environmental changes and adaptation to stress, including changes in osmolarity, acid stress, SOS induction, and anaerobiosis [19194530, 19127382].
HU binds DNA without sequence specificity and with low affinity, but at low concentrations HU induces bends and at high concentrations HU induces  formation of rigid filaments [10508175, 2001682, 10519118, 10551881, 18586040]. <ACTCONDN> binding of this protein is destabilized when  tension of  double helix increases</ACTCONDN> [21427084].
 effects of HU protein enhancements on DNA flexibility and  cyclization rate have been determined, based on a Monte Carlo approach, by Czapla et al. [21459097].
Review: [22387214].
</SUMMARY>