<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
NikR,  Nickel-responsive repressor,  is a tetramer and <DOM>consists of two domains.  crystal structures of  C-terminal domain, apo-NikR, nickel-activated NikR, and NikR in complex with its operator DNA have been solved [12970756, 16945905, 18193897].  C-terminal 83 amino acids form  tetrameric core, which carries  high-affinity nickel-binding site and resembles  ACT fold of <EVF> ACT (aspartokinase, chorismate mutase, TyrA) family</EVF>. Two N-terminal domains intertwine to form a dimeric DNA-binding ribbon-helix-helix (RHH) domain [10595554].  two RHH DNA-binding domains flank  tetrameric core of  protein [16945905].
 NikR tetramer contains four high-affinity nickel-binding sites located at  subunit interfaces of  C-terminal domain and additional low-affinity metal-binding sites </DOM>[12401498, 12401490, 17397155, 18379702, 16945905, 15287730].  coordination of  nickel ion binding to  high-affinity site depends on binding to DNA. <ACTEFFE> nickel ion is bound in a four-coordinate planar conformation to NikR in solution and in a six-coordinate conformation to NikR bound to DNA</ACTEFFE> [12524532]. Based on crystal structure and mutation analyses, it was determined that  <DOM>K64 and R65 residues are crucial for  NikR functions</DOM> on  nikAp1 promoter in vivo [22971172].
NikR mediates two levels of repression. Saturation of  high-affinity nickel-binding sites at nickel concentrations in  picomolar range leads to substantial binding to  nik operator and a low level of constitutive repression, while nickel binding to  low-affinity sites at higher nickel concentrations (in  nanomolar range) leads to a large increase in operator binding and strong repression [12401498, 18193897, 19319388]. <DOM>His48 and His110 are  residues that participate in  low-affinity Ni(II)-binding response [20583753].
In addition to  four high-affinity nickel-binding sites,  crystal structure reveals two binding sites for potassium ions, bridging  metal- and DNA-binding domains [16945905]. It is still disputed wher se sites actually resemble  low-affinity binding sites for nickel ions or wher se sites function as potassium-binding sites [15826657, 16945905].</DOM> Molecular simulations on  EcNikR structure suggest that <ACTCONDP>binding of NikR to DNA is more favorable when NikR contains K+</ACTCONDP> [19621966] and  allosterically activated DNA-binding conformation of NikR is stabilized by K+ [16945905, 19621966]. Moreover, <ACTCONDN>DNA binding of NikR is abolished in  absence of K+</ACTCONDN> [20088519].
Reviews: [10648098, 16504569, 22970729].
</SUMMARY>