<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
<TUCREG>PhoB is a dual transcription regulator that <ACTREG>activates expression of  Pho regulon in response to environmental Pi</ACTREG>. </TUCREG>  Pho regulon includes operons and genes whose products are involved in <RP>phosphorus uptake and metabolism [8432742, 8755861, 17020555]. Expression of  periplasmic binding proteins for peptide transport</RP>, OppA and DppA, is repressed by PhoB [1478454].  
PhoB is a response regulator and belongs to  two-component system PhoR/PhoB. <ACTCONDP>Under phosphate limitation conditions  inner membrane sensor kinase PhoR autophosphorylates. Subsequent transfer of  phosphate group to PhoB results in activation of PhoB</ACTCONDP> [2693738]. <ACTCONDN>When phosphate is in excess, autophosphorylation of PhoR is inhibited and PhoB-P is dephosphorylated</ACTCONDN>. This negative regulation requires in addition to PhoR an intact Pst system and PhoU [8691745]. In  absence of PhoR, cross-regulation of PhoB by CreC or acetyl phosphate results in phosphorylation of PhoB in response to carbon sources [1551836, 2228961]. 
<DOM>PhoB consists of two functional domains,  N-terminal receiver domain, which is phosphorylated, and  C-terminal output domain, which binds to DNA and interacts with  ?70-subunit of RNA polymerase to activate transcription [8648643, 8422984].  crystal structure of a subcomplex, which includes  ?4 domain of  ?70 factor fused with  RNAP ?-subunit flap tip helix, shows that  ?4 domain is recruited to  pho box promoters by PhoB and reorients  ?4 domain with respect to its binding site [21829166].  output domain belongs to  winged helix-turn-helix family of transcription factors [9199401]. <REG>Its activity is silenced by  receiver domain, and phosphorylation relieves inhibition</REG> [11073900].</DOM>  3D structure has been solved for  receiver domain [9878437] and two constitutively active mutants of this domain [17182055] as well as that for  output domain [9016718]. Aspartic acid 196 (D196) and arginine 219 (R219), located in  C-terminal DNA-binding domain minor groove, are necessary for  binding process for  PhoB transcriptional regulator [21912786]. Based on biochemical analysis, a positive cooperative binding mechanism of PhoBDBD (DNA-binding domain) to its cognate DNA sequence and a decisive contribution of dimerization to  complex stability were demonstrated [24199636].
PhoB binds to  Pho box, which has been described as <SSA><SSM><SSZ>two direct 11-bp repeats</SSZ></SSM> consisting of <SSM>successive 7-bp direct repeats</SSM> followed by an A/T-rich region of 4 bp, situated 10 bp upstream of  -10 region</SSA> [3054125, 12015152, 3537313].  pho promoters contain functional  -10 sequences but lack  consensus  -35 sequence [2651888].
 3D structures of  receiver domain in  absence and presence of  phosphoryl analog beryllium fluoride [16154092, 9878437] and of two constitutively active mutants of this domain [17182055] have been solved.  data reveal that  active and inactive receiver domains dimerize in two different orientations relative to each or. Also,  3D structures of  output domain without DNA [10653699] and in complex with its target DNA have been solved [12015152]. se data reveal that  output domains bind in a novel tandem arrangement, in which several monomers bind head to tail to successive 11-bp direct repeat sequences, coating one face of  double helix [12015152]. In addition, a hybrid protein, in which  receiver domain has been replaced by a leucine zipper, is active in vivo as a transcriptional activator [19371748]. 
Taken toger se data suggest that <ACTREG>PhoB is activated through an intermolecular mechanism</ACTREG>. In unphosphorylated PhoB  output domains are constrained. <ACTCONF>Phosphorylation changes  relative orientation of  subunits to each or, such that orientational constraints between  output domains are lost, allowing  tandem head-to-tail orientation for  active conformation</ACTCONF> [16154092, 19371748, 12015152].
</SUMMARY>