<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Transcriptional activator EvgA initiates a complex activation cascade for gene products involved in acid resistance and multidrug resistance [19352034, 14523115, 15489450, 12670992, 12399493, 15494746].
It directly activates at least six operons, among which  b1500-ydeO operon encodes two additional activator proteins. B1500 is  connector protein for  PhoPQ two-component system, which is involved in acid resistance and Mg2+ homeostasis [17998538]. YdeO is an AraC-like transcriptional activator for at least 12 operons, including  gadE-mdtE-mdtF operon [19329985, 19329985, 12694615, 11282467]. mdtEF encodes a <RP>multidrug efflux pump</RP>, and gadE encodes  master regulator for glutamate-dependent acid resistance [12940989, 19220752]. GadE activates transcription of two additional AraC-like transcriptional activators, GadX and GadW.  EvgA-YdeO-GadE circuit is very complex and <ACTREG>involves feedback loops and autoactivation</ACTREG> [15489450, 19352034, 17660422]. <ACTCONDP>It is activated during exponential growth in acidified minimal medium</ACTCONDP> and enables  cell to survive gastric acidity.
EvgA <EVF>belongs to  two-component system EvgS/EvgA</EVF> [1289796] which is highly homologous to  virulence-related BvgAS system of Bordetella pertussis.  sensor kinase EvgS carries an N-terminal periplasmic domain and three cytoplasmic domains, a transmitter, a receiver, and a phosphotransfer (HPt) domain. EvgA is a <EVF>member of  NarL subfamily of response regulators</EVF>, <DOM>consisting of an N-terminal receiver domain and a C-terminal helix-turn-helix DNA-binding domain. Like BvgA, EvgA presumably is phosphorylated in a phosphorelay reaction that involves phosphotransfer from  autophosphorylated transmitter domain to  receiver and Hpt domain of EvgS and finally to  receiver domain of EvgA [9501520, 11111905, 9535079].</DOM>
<SSA>An <SSZ>18-bp <SSM>inverted repeat motif</SSM></SSZ> was proposed as  EvgA DNA-binding site</SSA> [12399493, 14523115].
</SUMMARY>