<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
NarL,  nitrate/nitrite response regulator NarL,  is a transcriptional dual regulator of many <RP>anaerobic electron transport and fermentation-related genes in  response to  availability of high concentrations of nitrate or nitrite [9230919, 7855431]. NarL activates expression of 51 operons in response to nitrate, mostly genes needed for nitrate respiration. NarL represses 41 operons involved in alternative respiratory pathways, such as fumarate reduction or fermentation of simple sugars</RP> [16377617].
response regulator NarL <EVF>belongs to  LuxR/UhpA family</EVF> [2559300, 2314271] and is part of  two-component system NarX-NarL. re is intensive cross-regulation with  paralogous two-component system NarQ-NarP [12546643, 8501030]. Each of  sensors, NarX and NarQ, is able to phosphorylate NarL and NarP, leading to  activation of both proteins. In  absence of nitrate and nitrite, NarX and NarQ stimulate  dephosphorylation of NarL-P and NarP-P [8051011, 8473280]. This reaction is specific, that is, <ACTREG>NarL-P is only desphosphorylated by NarX</ACTREG>. <ACTREG> system discriminates between nitrate and nitrite. In  presence of nitrate both sensors phosphorylate NarL and NarP to  same extent. In  presence of nitrite, NarX phosphorylates NarP but acts primarily as a phosphatase for NarL-P</ACTREG> [9426129, 9006026, 10464202]. In contrast, NarQ phosphorylates NarL and NarP in response to both nitrate and nitrite. refore, NarL mainly serves as a nitrate regulator and is only weakly phosphorylated in  presence of nitrite [10464202, 10542156].
<DOM>NarL consists of  N-terminal receiver domain and a C-terminal DNA-binding domain.  crystal structures of  monomeric full-length protein [8780507, 9521685] and of  dimeric output domain bound to DNA [12352954, 16262254] have been solved. In unphosphorylated NarL,  DNA-binding site of  output domain is blocked by  receiver domain [8780507]. Phosphorylation induces  separation of both domains, resulting in  exposure of previously inaccessible DNA-binding residues and  formation of a new dimerization interface in  C-terminal domain [12484754, 12614149].
 receiver domain of NarL and NarP could function as a stabilizer of  carboxyl-terminal domain (CTD); it enhances DNA binding and/or enables repression per se in vivo. In addition,  receiver may make protein-protein contacts necessary for transcription activation [20634237].</DOM>
 NarL <SSA>consensus recognition sequence consists of a <SSZ>7-bp element</SSZ>, termed  NarL heptamer</SSA> [8437517, 8736541]. A subset of NarL-binding sites, in which two inverted repeats of  heptamer are separated by 2 bp (termed 7-2-7 sites), also represents binding sites for NarP [9302020, 7854119]. refore,  NarL and NarP regulons overlap. <SSA>NarL-binding heptamers are found as single copies, inverted repeats, or direct repeats at positions between +20 and -200 relative to  transcriptional start sites </SSA>[7643383]. Most NarL-dependent promoters are also codependent on  oxygen sensor FNR, IHF, or Fis, implying that multiprotein complexes are involved in  transcriptional regulation of NarL target promoters [16936015, 9484902, 10972841, 15225315, 11929525].
 Nar sites are classified based on  location of  activator binding site (ref). Nar class I promoters have a single Nar-binding site immediately adjacent to  promoter [17720788, 19245365, 16199562] and Nar class II promoters have two Nar-binding sites upstream of  promoter [20634237] and reference rein.
 </SUMMARY>