<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
LrhA,  LysR homologue A,  regulates  transcription of genes involved in  synsis of <RP>type 1 fimbriae [16207912]. Indirectly, this protein also regulates  transcription of several genes involved in motility, chemotaxis, and flagellum synsis</RP> by directly controlling  expression of  master regulator FlhDC [12123461]. 
On  or hand, LrhA also regulates negatively and partially   translation of rpoS through two mechanisms, one of which is RprA dependent and  or one is RprA independent. RprA is a small RNA that regulates positively  translation of rpoS. Both mechanisms of regulation require  presence of  sRNA chaperone Hfq; refore, it was suggested that anor small RNA , in addition to RprA , that regulates rpoS translation is regulated by LrhA [16621809].
LrhA is a protein that <EVF>belongs to  LysR family</EVF> and, like  members of this family, <DOM> LrhA contains three different domains: an N-terminal helix-turn-helix domain for DNA binding, a coinducer recognition domain in  center of  protein, and a C-terminal domain that contains a cluster of four cysteine and  two histidine residues [7565112].</DOM>  activity of most members of this family is controlled by  small molecules; however,  effector of LrhA was not known until now [12123461]. <EVPIT>LrhA has high degree of homology  to HexA from Erwinia carotovora (64% identity ) and PecT from Erwinia chrysanmi (61% identity)</EVPIT> [9643539, 8626286].
LrhA appears to recognize and <SSA>bind  to a partial <SSZ><SSM>palindromic DNA sequence</SSM>  of 13 bp</SSZ> that shows low similarity  to  general consensus for LysR family members</SSA> [12123461].
<TUR> lrhA gene is transcribed alone, and it is under positive autoregulation by LrhA</TUR>.  Unlike  majority of LysR-type regulators, LrhA does not regulate  expression of adjacent genes to lrhA [12123461]. <TUCREG> expression of lrhA is repressed by  RcsCDB phosphorelay system and by  DNA motor protein FtsK</TUCREG> [16621809].
</SUMMARY>