<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
N-ethylmaleimide reductase repressor,  [18567656] represses  nemA gene, which is involved in <RP>reductive degradation of N-ethylmaleimide (NEM) and or toxic nitrous compounds</RP>, and <TUR>it also represses its own expression</TUR>. NemR <EVF>belongs to  TetR family of HTH-type DNA-binding transcription factors</EVF> [16397293, 15556475].
NemR binds to a <SSA>region <SSZ>16 bp in length</SSZ>, and its consensus is a <SSM>palindromic sequence</SSM>, TAGACCnnnnGGTCTA</SSA>, which is referred as  NemR box [18567656]. This box sequence, TAGACCnnnnGGTCTA, is close to  recognition sequence, TTGACCAnnTGGTCAA, of RutR ( RutR box). RutR can bind upstream of  nemRA operon; however, it does not play an important role in regulation of nemRA expression in vivo [18567656].
Presently,  nemRA operon is  unique member of  NemR regulon. Based on genomic SELEX and gene expression analyses, NemR could be affecting or genes, such as ydhF-ydhL, gloA, sapABCDF, yeaU, pck  yeaT, and yhgE [18567656] however,  regulation of  genes under control of NemR requires more detailed studies before it can be solved.
 NemRA system plays an important role in Escherichia coli survival in  presence of  toxic compound N-ethylmaleimide (NEM), which is  inducer for depression of  nemRA operon [18567656]. It has been experimentally verified that methylglyoxal (MG) and not NEM is  real inducer for <TUL> nemRA operon</TUL> [23646895]. This induction was determined by ChIP-chip analysis with DNA-RNAP occupancy when cells were exposed to growth-inhibitory concentrations of MG [23646895]. NemR is a transcriptional repressor that is sensitive to HOCl and related reactive chlorine species (RCS), and its gene products contribute to increased bleach resistance by detoxifying reactive electrophiles produced during this process [23536188].
<ACTREG> NemR regulator is controlled by alkylation of one or more of its Cys residues</ACTREG>. <DOM> NemR contains five Cys residues, at positions 70, 78, 88, 121, and 125, in a total of 199 residues. In some of se residues, NemR is controlled by alkylation [18567656]. On  or hand, Lee et al. (2013) reported that NemR contains six cysteines located at residue positions 21, 98, 106, 116, 149, and 153 [23506073].  critical Cys residue(s) involved in NemR activity control remains to be identified [18567656]. However,  cysteines at positions 21 and 116 have been determined as essential in sensing electrophiles in vivo and in vitro [23506073].  Cys-106 residue, which is conserved among NemR homologs, has been identified as a trigger for  NemR RCS-sensing mechanism [23536188].</DOM> NemR is also a redox-regulated transcriptional repressor, since it uses  oxidation status of HOCl-sensitive cysteine residues to respond to bleach and related reactive chlorine species [23536188]. 
Review: [15944459].
</SUMMARY>