<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Lrp,  Leucine-responsive regulatory protein,  is a dual transcriptional regulator for at least 10% of  genes in Escherichia coli [12374860]. se genes are involved in <RP>amino acid biosynsis and catabolism, nutrient transport, pili synsis, and or cellular functions, including 1-carbon metabolism</RP> [1346534, 12675791, 7968922]. In addition, Lrp affects nearly three-fourths of  genes induced upon entry into stationary phase[12374860, 19052235]. Lrp might also play a topological role in dynamic DNA packaging [8212136].
Lrp can act as a repressor or activator for its target genes. <ACTREG>Binding of leucine can affect se activities in three different ways: <ACTEFFE>leucine</ACTEFFE> eir potentiates, antagonizes, or has no discernible effect upon Lrp action</ACTREG> [1532173, 8432705, 8561478]. It is believed that Lrp senses  presence of rich nutrition based on  concentration of leucine and positively regulates genes that function during famine and negatively regulates genes that function during a feast [7968922].
Lrp forms a mixture of octamers and hexadecamers [11575919]. <ACTCONDP>In  presence of leucine  octamer configuration is favored</ACTCONDP>. It is believed that  switch between  octameric and hexadecameric states modulated by leucine affects  binding and  activity of Lrp at its target genes [12054800]. <ACTCONF> structure of Lrp from Escherichia coli bound to DNA as an octamer has been solved [17223133]. Lrp forms an open ring structure, in which  DNA is wrapped around  octamer in a nucleosome-like structure</ACTCONF>. <DOM> monomer chain contains two domains, an N-terminal helix-turn-helix motif and a C-terminal αβ-sandwich fold.</DOM> 
Lrp-regulated promoters commonly contain multiple adjacent binding sites for  protein with low sequence specificity. A consensus recognition sequence has been described [8636076]. <SSA> identified <SSZ>15-bp sequence motif</SSZ> is structured with flanking CAG/CTG triplets and a central AT-rich signal</SSA>. Leucine has two effects upon binding to DNA in vitro:  affinity of Lrp is reduced but  cooperativity of binding to multiple sites is increased [15571719].
Lrp <EVF>belongs to  Lrp/AsnC family of transcriptional regulatory proteins</EVF>, which is widely distributed throughout  eubacterial and archaeal domains. Lrp appears to be very well conserved in members of  γ-proteobacteria [12675791].
</SUMMARY>