<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
transcriptional activator GadX, for  Glutamic acid decarboxylase,  <ACTREG>is positively autoregulated</ACTREG> and controls  transcription of pH-inducible genes, including  principal acid resistance system [12686161, 11976288, 11555293] is glutamate dependent (GAD), is also referred to as  GAD system, and its genes are involved in <RP>multidrug efflux</RP> [12446650, 18808381, 12730179, 16980449, 18297445]. In addition GadX also activates  transcription of   central activator involved in  acid response [17660422].  physiological inducer is unknown. Richard et al. proposed that GadX can sense intracellular Na+ concentrations, but  mechanism is not known [17768258].
GadX is one of  regulators of  acid resistance system and is encoded by  unusual <TUL>gadXW operon, which is located in  region called  acid fitness island</TUL> [18808381]. <TURO>This operon encodes two transcriptional regulators, GadX and GadW</TURO>, both of which are <EVF>members of  AraC/XylS family of transcriptional regulators</EVF> [9409145, 11282467, 18808381]. 
 activities of GadX and GadW are indispensable upon entry into  stationary phase in response to acid pH  [11976288, 12446650]. In addition Tramonti et al. provided evidence that  transcription of  gadXW operon is regulated to a posttranscriptional level by a gadY small RNA [18808381, 15466020].
<EVPIT>GadX is highly homologous to GadW (42%)</EVPIT>, and apparently both are capable of cross talk to regulate expression of  genes of this system [18808381]. Although little is known about  regulating mechanism of GadX, Tucker et al. proposed that this regulator and GadW have distinct molecular mechanisms [12730179, 16980449]. se regulators form homodimers [9409145] and heterodimers [12446650]in vivo.
Currently,   GadW/GadX-dependent circuit, involved in  GAD system, is under discussion and study. Tramonti et al.  showed that GadX alone activates  gadA and gadB promoters [11976288]. Ma et al. added to this regulatory interaction  GadW protein, showing that it inhibits GadX and that in some cases it activates in  absence of GadX  [12446650]. Trucker et al. provided evidence that <ACTREG>GadW can work as a coactivator of GadX or it can inhibit  GadX-dependent activation</ACTREG>, along with evidence of more target genes for GadX/GadW regulation  [12730179]. About ir interactions, Tramonti et al. showed  direct GadX binding at  promoters of  gadB (two sites) and gadA (four sites) operons [11976288] also, Ma et al. showed that GadW forms a homodimer and that it also binds to  DNA of  gadA and gadB promoters  [12446650]. 
As a member of  AraC/XylS family, <DOM>this transcription factor is composed of two domains:  C-terminal domain <EVPIDT>(60% homologous to  C terminal of GadW)</EVPIDT>, which contains two potential helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motifs in  DNA-binding region, and  amino-terminal domain (<EVPIDT>30% homologous to  N terminal of GadW</EVPIDT>), which is responsible for dimerization [9409145, 8451183, 12446650]. </DOM>
Tramonti et al. speculated that GadX binds in tandem to two directed repeat sequences, in  same orientation, in  intergenic regions to activate or represses  transcription of  genes regulated [18808381]. <SSA> binding targets for GadX consist of <SSZ>21-nucleotide-long <SSM>directed repeat sequences</SSM></SSZ> that possess conserved motifs, called  GAD box, which is proposed to be  binding site for GadX and GadW</SSA> [12730179, 12730179, 18808381]. This proposal was not unexpected, because  identity and similarity of  C-terminal domains are 41% and 66%,  respectively [18808381]. Each monomer of GadX binds to one of se conserved sequences [18808381].
</SUMMARY>