<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
transcription factor FhlA, for  Formate hydrogen lyase Activator,  <ACTREG>is positively autoregulated</ACTREG> and controls  transcription of  operons involved in  <RP>formate metabolism to produce dihydrogen and carbon dioxide</RP> [2118503, 3056900, 2280686, 1779767, 8412675, 8034728, 17938909, 17668201, 8034727]. <ACTCONDP>Transcription of this operon is induced when E. coli is grown under anaerobic growth conditions and when  physiological inducer, formate, binds to  FhlA protein</ACTCONDP> [1779767, 8412675, 2118503, 8034727]. <ACTCONDP><ACTCONF>When formate binds to FhlA,  protein becomes active</ACTCONF> as  binding affinity of FhlA increases</ACTCONDP>, and it activates  transcription of σ54-dependent promoters. 
<ACTCONDN>HycA may inactivate  function of  FhlA protein and prevent  binding of FhlA to target sequences</ACTCONDN>, but  mechanism of  negative regulation by HycA is unknown [1625581, 17938909].
<ACTREG>FhlA is subject to posttranscriptional regulation by  sRNA OxyS</ACTREG> [12753181, 10903857, 9774350]. This sRNA binds to FhlA mRNA and inhibits translation by interfering with  binding of  mRNA and  ribosome  [9230301, 10903857, 9774350].
As <EVF>a member of  group of σ54-dependent transcriptional regulators</EVF>, <DOM>FhlA contains three domains: a possible sensory domain located in  N terminus that probably modulates  activity of  C-terminal domain [11700359, 7751289]  central domain, which is probably involved in open complex formation, ATP hydrolysis, and interaction with σ54 and formate [1833069, 7751289, 8981978] and  C-terminal domain, which contains a helix-turn-helix motif for DNA binding [10848985].</DOM> <EVPIT>FhlA shows 46% identity to  HyfR protein</EVPIT>, a member of  same group. se proteins are dissimilar in ir N-terminal regions, which in FhlA recognizes formate. However, y show only one different residue in ir helix-turn-helix motifs, suggesting that y recognize similar DNA-binding sites [9387241].
Leonhartsberger et al suggested that this protein <SSA>binds to degenerate regions <SSZ>16 bp in length</SSZ> (CATTTCGTACGAAATG)</SSA> [10848985]. However, alignments made by  curators of this database showed that  sequence is less conserved in  upstream regions regulated. This result also showed that  motif TGTCGnnnnTGACA is conserved in  sequences examined, and for this reason  binding sites for FhlA regulation have been relocated, reassigned, and corrected.
 consensus sequence TGTCGnnnnTGACA is in agreement with alignments determined by  curator for se upstream regions and with  corresponding evidence obtained in  bibliography of every operon, including similarity to  consensus sequence and  data from footprinting assays, computational analysis, and profiling of FhlA-dependent gene expression [8034728, 14702328].  <SSA>FhlA-binding sites are represented by an <SSM>inverted <SSZ>14-bp repeat</SSZ></SSM> motif</SSA>.
Review: [12753181].
</SUMMARY>