<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
ArgP,  arginine protein,  controls  transcription of genes involved in <RP>  arginine transport system and genes involved in DNA replication.</RP> DNA replication is also <TUR>regulated directly by <TUCREG>ArgP when it binds to three 13-mers located in  origin of replication (OriC)</TUCREG>, blocking  DNA opening by DnaA</TUR> and inhibiting this cellular process [2034653, 2208289, 1733927]. <ACTREG>DNA binding by ArgP is prevented when  serine protease Do (DegP) hydrolyzes this transcriptional regulator</ACTREG> [8335089].
ArgP was first identified as an inhibitor of oriC-initiated DNA replication in vitro. It has also subsequently been described as a nucleoid-associated protein that shows apparently sequence-nonspecific DNA-binding activity [10551881].
ArgP is a noncanonical regulator, as it binds to a number of additional sites in  genome without an apparent direct regulatory effect, exhibiting low-affinity binding to se sites [21890697, 1733927, 21441513].
To activate transcription, ArgP <SSA>recognizes AT-rich DNA-binding sites</SSA>, but no consensus sequence has been identified. When this protein activates genes involved in replication, <ACTEFFE>it appears to bind to ir regulatory regions without a coeffector</ACTEFFE> [9254708, 9819053]. However, <ACTREG> activity of ArgP depends on arginine and lysine to regulate genes involved in arginine metabolism</ACTREG>. se amino acids, which bind to ArgP, do not seem to help  protein to form dimers or to bind to DNA, but y contribute to recruitment of  RNA polymerase and in forming  open complex. However, only  ArgP-arginine complex can produce transcripts, whereas ArgP-lysine appears to inhibit transcription [17504942, 15150242].
ArgP is a dimer with an estimated concentration of 100 to 400 molecules per cell (that is, around 200 to 800 nM monomers) [10515926, 1733927].
<DOM>ArgP, which <EVF>belongs to  LysR family</EVF>, has a helix-turn-helix motif located close to  N terminus.</DOM> <EVF>Members of  LysR family that show considerable homology to ArgP are AmpR from Citrobacter freundii, MetR from Salmonella enterica serotype Typhimurium, and NhaR from Pseudomonas putida</EVF>[2034653].
 expression of argP is induced by PhoB under phosphate starvation [10589831]. Contrary to  suggestion made by [10600368], [15150242] has suggested that  argP is not autoregulated.
ArgP is also called IciA ( for  inhibitor of chromosome initiation ) [2034653].
</SUMMARY>