<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
NarP,  nitrate/nitrite response regulator NarP,  is a transcriptional dual regulator of many <RP>anaerobic electron transport and fermentation</RP>-related genes in  response to  availability of high concentrations of nitrate or nitrite [9230919, 7855431]. A microarray analysis suggests that NarP activates 14 operons and represses 37 operons [16377617, 16417494].
response regulator NarP <EVF>belongs to  LuxR/UhpA family</EVF> [2559300, 2314271] and is part of  two-component system NarQ-NarP. re is intensive cross-regulation with  paralogous two-component system NarX-NarL [12546643, 8501030]. Each of  sensors, NarQ and NarX, phosphorylates both NarP and NarL, leading to  activation of both proteins. <ACTREG>In  absence of nitrate and nitrite, NarX and NarQ stimulate  dephosphorylation of NarL-P and NarP-P</ACTREG> [8051011, 8473280]. This reaction is specific, that is, <ACTREG>NarP-P is only dephosphorylated by NarQ</ACTREG>.  system discriminates between nitrate and nitrite. In  presence of nitrate both sensors phosphorylate NarL and NarP to  same extent. In  presence of nitrite, autophosphorylation of NarX is low and NarX acts primarily as a phosphatase for NarL-P [9426129, 9006026, 10464202]. In contrast, NarQ phosphorylates NarL and NarP in response to both nitrate and nitrite. refore, with nitrite, NarP-P is  major regulator, and with nitrate both NarL and NarP are functional [10464202, 10542156].
<DOM>NarP consists of  N-terminal receiver domain and a C-terminal DNA-binding domain.  receiver domain of NarL and NarP could function as a stabilizer of  carboxyl-terminal domain (CTD); it enhances DNA binding and/or enables repression per se in vivo. In addition,  receiver may make protein-protein contacts necessary for transcription activation [20634237].</DOM>
NarP consists of  N-terminal receiver domain and a C-terminal DNA-binding domain. <EVPIT>NarP is 44% homologous to NarL</EVPIT>,  structure of which has been solved by X-ray crystallography [8780507, 9521685]. NarL and NarP work toger in  regulation of gene expression. NarP <SSA>binds to <SSM>two inverted heptamers</SSM> separated by 2 bp, termed 7-2-7 sites</SSA> [9302020, 7854119]. <SSA> binding sites for NarP overlap with  binding sites for NarL</SSA>. However, for NarL  presence of one heptamer is sufficient for binding [8437517, 8736541].  location and spacing of  binding sites vary considerably in different promoters, and most promoters are also codependent on additional regulators, e.g.,  oxygen sensor FNR, IHF, or Fis [16936015, 9484902]. 
 Nar sites are classified based on  location of  activator binding site (ref). Nar class I promoters have a single Nar-binding site immediately adjacent to  promoter [17720788, 19245365, 16199562] and Nar class II promoters have two Nar-binding sites upstream of  promoter [20634237]and reference re in.
NarP acts as a repressor or activator of gene expression, or it interferes with or regulatory proteins bound near  promoter. For example, <TUR>expression of nrf is activated by FNR and repressed by IHF and Fis</TUR>. NarL and NarP act as antirepressors. <ACTCONDP>In  presence of nitrate or nitrite NarL or NarP binds to a target site upstream of  binding sites for FNR, IHF, and Fis</ACTCONDP>, counteracting  effect of IHF but not that of Fis. Similarly, activation of nir by FNR is suppressed by IHF, Fis, and H-NS. NarL or NarP counteracts repression by Fis and IHF, but not repression by H-NS [10972841, 16936015, 15978080, 10972841]. Expression of  napF operon is induced by NarP in  presence of FNR. NarL can displace NarP but is unable to activate transcription from this location [9696769, 7643383].  ydh operon is activated by FNR and suppressed by NarP and NarL. It has been suggested that NarL is responsible for nitrate-mediated repression and NarP is responsible for nitrite-mediated repression of ydh, and both compete with RNA polymerase for binding at  promoter [18227264].
</SUMMARY>