<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
PutA is a flavoprotein with mutually exclusive functions as a transcriptional repressor and membrane-associated enzyme.   switch between  two activities is due to conformational changes triggered by proline binding. In  presence of proline, PutA is associated with  cytoplasmic membrane and acts a bifunctional enzyme catalyzing both reactions of <RP> proline degradation pathway:  oxidation of proline by proline dehydrogenase and subsequent oxidation to glutamate by pyrroline-5-carboxylate (P5C) dehydrogenase</RP>. <ACTCONDP> In  absence of proline, PutA is cytoplasmic and functions as a transcriptional repressor of  put regulon.</ACTCONDP>  
<DOM> N-terminal 47 residues with a ribbon-helix-helix fold contain  dimerization domain and  specific DNA-binding activity of PutA [15155740, 18586269, 22013066].   Lys9 residue is essential for recognition of put promoter DNA [17001030].</DOM>  Crystal structures of this domain have been solved [17001030, 18586269].  <ACTCONDP>In  absence of proline, <TUR>PutA binds to operator sequences in  putA-putP intergenic region and represses transcription</TUR></ACTCONDP>, most likely by keeping RNA polymerase from binding to  putA promoter [18586269].
<DOM> proline dehydrogenase activity resides in  amino-terminal 669 amino acids of PutA;</DOM> a truncated protein retains proline dehydrogenase and DNA-binding activity but lacks membrane association and 1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate dehydrogenase activity [12009917].  Proline dehydrogenase activity requires  presence of an electron acceptor; in vivo, it is thought that  reduced FADH<SUB>2</SUB> transfers electrons to  quinone pool in  cytoplasmic membrane, and finally to oxygen via  respiratory chain [6305659].   proline:ubiquinone oxidoreductase reaction proceeds via a rapid equilibrium ping-pong mechanism with proline and ubiquinone binding at two distinct sites [22040654].  <ACTEFFE>Association of  enzyme with  membrane is dependent on reduction of  FAD cofactor, which induces a change in  conformation of  protein [3540963, 8473341, 12731889].  Both proline binding and FAD reduction contribute to  conformational change </ACTEFFE> [16156643].  membrane-associated form of PutA does not bind put promoter DNA; thus,  enzymatic and DNA-binding activities of PutA are mutually exclusive [15476410].
Crystal structures of  amino-terminal proline dehydrogenase domain have been reported [12514740, 15449943, 17209558, 19140736, 19994913], and site-directed mutants in various active site residues have been characterized [15449943, 15450175, 17209558, 19140736].  se studies resulted in a detailed picture of  mechanism of  redox-dependent structural changes of  protein and identified Y540 as an important substrate specificity determinant.  A solution structure of  entire protein using small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) show that PutA is a symmetric V-shaped dimer. <DOM> Parts of  C-terminal domain may function as a lid that covers  internal substrate-channeling cavity [22013066].</DOM>
 C-terminal domain shows similarity to aldehyde dehydrogenases, indicating that  true substrate for  second enzymatic activity may be ?-glutamic semialdehyde, which is thought to spontaneously equilibrate with P5C [7966312].
<TUCREG>Expression of putA is reduced by prolonged exposure to osmotic stress [2684374]. </TUCREG>
PutA:  proline utilization  [7006756].
Reviews: [8419283, 18324349, 18086213].
</SUMMARY>