<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
NorR,  NO reduction and detoxification Regulator,  is one of several regulatory proteins, such as Fur, SoxR, and OxyR, that are involved in  response to reactive nitrogen species. <ACTCONDP>Under anaerobic and microaerobic conditions it activates transcription of  norVW operon</ACTCONDP>, encoding <RP>a nitric oxide (NO)-reducing flavorubredoxin that detoxifies NO</RP> [16100392, 14718666, 12529359, 11751865, 12142437].  
A norR mutant is completely defective with respect to anaerobic NO detoxification [11751865] and is sensitive to reactive nitrogen intermediates generated from nitroprusside. <TUR> norR gene is transcribed divergently from norVW and autoregulated</TUR> [16417519]. <TUCREG>It is activated in  absence of oxygen and by nitrite under anaerobic conditions</TUCREG> [12586421]. 
<DOM>NorR is a σ54-dependent transcriptional activator [12618438]. It contains three domains: an N-terminal GAF (cGMP phosphodiesterase, adenylate cyclase, FhlA) domain that is involved in signal sensing [16193057, 12529359, 11032796] a central catalytic AAA+ domain that is required for interacting with σ54 and for coupling ATP hydrolysis to promoter DNA melting by RNA polymerase; and a C-terminal domain that contains a helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motif [18003617].  
<ACTREG>In  absence of NO,  activity of  central catalytic AAA+ domain of NorR is repressed by direct interaction between  GAF domain and  σ54-interacting region of  AAA+ domain. This interaction prevents access to  σ54-RNA polymerase complex [20624215]. Binding of NO relieves intramolecular repression and activates  ATPase activity of  central AAA+ domain</ACTREG> [18433632, 16193057].  GAF domain contains a mononuclear nonheme iron center that binds NO reversibly [16193057]. Spectroscopy studies and structural modeling of  GAF domain identified five candidate ligands for  nonheme iron and suggested a model in which it is coordinated in a pseudo-octahedral environment by three aspartate residues, an arginine, and a cysteine [18003617].  iron oxidation state influences  activation of NorR [22563051]. </DOM> 
 intergenic region of norR and norVW carries <SSA>three binding sites for NorR with a <SSM>symmetrical <SSZ>11-bp consensus sequence</SSZ></SSM></SSA> [15667300]. se sites act as enhancer-binding sites for transcriptional activation by NorR [15375149, 15547270]. All three sites are required for  stimulation of  ATPase activity in vitro and activation of norV expression in vivo [19955233]. 
Based on biochemical experiments and electron micrographs using a norR mutant carrying a deletion of  N-terminal domain, it has been proposed that NorR binds as a hexameric ring to DNA [19955233].  data furr suggest that in contrast to or enhancer-binding proteins  DNA binding per se induces a conformational change in NorR that promotes hexameric ring formation. Presumably  hexamer is furr stabilized by additional DNA wrapped around  ring. <DOM>Binding of NO to  GAF domain relieves intramolecular repression of  central domain, leading to  activation of  ATPase activity and interaction with σ54 RNA polymerase [19955233].</DOM>
Reviews: [18433632, 17313521, 16417519]. 
</SUMMARY>