<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
The response regulator OmpR, for  Outer membrane protein Regulator,  [6263866, 7042694, 17628138] belongs to the two-component system EnvZ/OmpR [1700256, 1311295, 1618729, 7855421, 10192921, 10947842, 11973328, 12077136, 12453214, 15979641, 16553882, 12453215]. EnvZ is an osmosensor histidine kinase and is known to be a transmembrane protein composed of three domains: an external sensory domain (amino terminal), a cytoplasmic transmitter domain (carboxyl terminal), and a transmembrane hydrophobic central domain [2668953, 9070221, 15357641]. The sensor domain responds to changes in extracellular osmolarity. EnvZ and OmpR comprise a signal transduction system where the signal generated by the periplasmic receptor affects through a protein-protein interaction the EnvZ cytoplasmic component, which is transmitted via phosphorylation from autophosphorylating histidine kinase to the response regulator OmpR [1657696, 1700256, 1311295, 1618729, 7855421, 10192921, 10760160, 12453214, 15979641, 11934608, 11158569, 12453215]. 
<ACTCONF>Phosphorylated OmpR controls the transcriptional expression of several genes and operons</ACTCONF> whose products are involved in <RP>adaptation to changes in osmolarity, such as major outer membrane porins [3157679, 3010044, 3294816, 1741624, 1769957, 1618729, 8876642, 11973328, 16618701], and negatively regulates the expression of flagella [7642497] promotes biofilm formation [11717281] increases curli genes expression [9573197, 15743952] increases expression of several drug exporter genes [12618449] and confers increased beta-lactam resistance [12951338] among other effects </RP>[1695892, 10802181, 15175316, 18953042].
<DOM>This protein consists of two functional domains, the N-terminal receiver domain, which is phosphorylated, and the C-terminal output domain, which binds to DNA and interacts with the σ70 subunit of RNA polymerase to activate transcription [1321117, 7565603, 7568033, 8989318, 9016718, 9719640, 12077136, 15979641, 12077136, 15979641, 8989318]. The output domain belongs to the winged helix-turn-helix family of transcription factors [8989318, 9016718]. Its activity is silenced by the receiver domain, and phosphorylation relieves inhibition. </DOM>
The crystal structure of the DNA-binding domain has been determined at 1.95-? resolution [9016718] and also has been solved by NMR spectroscopy [18195018]. In addition, Rhee et al. identified the DNA-binding properties of the C-terminal of OmpR based on chemical shift changes and analysis of amino acid substitutions and base pair substitutions [18195018].
This regulator binds in tandem to <SSA>sequences that are <SSZ>20 nucleotides long</SSZ> and possess conserved motifs composed of two 10-bp <SSM>direct repeat subsites</SSM></SSA>; each dimer binds to one of these conserved sequences [1769957, 1321117, 8876642, 9719640, 11934608, 16618701, 8175665, 9878429, 7592927]. 
A model of regulation that explains the differential expression of porin genes has been described by Mattison et al. (2002) and by Yoshida et al. (2006) [11812125, 16618701, 11934608]. The investigators showed that in this model OmpR-P binds differentially and cooperatively to regulatory regions of the genes ompF and ompC[16618701, 9719640, 11812125, 11934608].
Under high-osmolarity conditions, ompF is repressed by DNA looping while the ompC gene is expressed, but under low-osmolarity conditions the effects on these genes are the reverse, i.e., ompC expression is repressed while ompF expression is increased [11934608, 16618701, 11812125, 9719640]. However, a potential mechanism for the phosphorylation-mediated activation of OmpR-regulated transcription follows the same pattern as with other <EVF>members of the OmpR/PhoB family of response regulators (RRs)</EVF> [23399542].
<ACTREG>The cross-regulation of OmpR by CpxA, ArcB, or acetyl phosphate results in phosphorylation of OmpR in response to different conditions [10947842, 18761686, 10192921].
Although in both Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium and Escherichia coli the OmpR transcriptional dual regulator is identical, its expression is regulated differently in the two bacterial species</ACTREG>, and there are very large differences in the composition of the OmpR regulon. In addition, the OmpR regulon evolved with different responses and roles in the two species during acid stress [24603618].
</SUMMARY>