<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
IHF,  Integration host factor,  is a global regulatory protein that helps to maintain <RP> DNA architecture. It binds and bends DNA at specific sites. IHF plays a role in DNA supercoilingand DNA duplex destabilization and affects processes such as DNA replication, recombination, and  expression of many genes</RP> [15102446, 1447969, 11827473].
IHF is highly abundant in  cell. Its total intracellular concentration varies with growth rate and is higher in exponential phase, with 6,000 dimers per cell, than in stationary phase (3,000 dimers per cell) [10515926].
IHF acts mostly as an accessory factor, stabilizing a correct nucleoprotein complex. For example, IHF was originally found to be required for  site-specific recombination of phage @@lambda@@ with  chromosome [6251971]. For this, IHF stabilizes  bending of  DNA to facilitate binding of  bivalent integrase molecules [2544029]. As anor example, IHF stimulates transcription at σ54-dependent promoters. Here, IHF acts to facilitate  formation of  loop between  upstream bound activator and  σ54 holoenzyme [2208275, 1404379]. 
Like HU, IHF plays a role in <RP>polyamine-dependent DNA condensation</RP>.  binding to low-affinity sites and introduction of sharp bends in chromosomal DNA promote  formation of rod-like condensed structures in chromosomal DNA [19132923]. 
IHF is a heterodimer consisting of  two subunits, IhfA (HimA) and IhfB (HimD, Hip), that share about 25% amino acid identity [3305480].  structure of IHF bound to DNA has been solved [8980235, 9032076]. <SSA>It binds tightly to <SSZ>DNA regions of about 40 bp</SSZ> carrying  13-bp consensus sequence with A/T-rich elements upstream of  core consensus sequence</SSA>. [2205834, 2972385, 8650000]. IHF makes no contact with  major groove and only a few contacts with  minor groove [2541927]. refore, specificity is believed to be due to  sequence-dependent structural parameters of  DNA, where A/T-rich regions play an important role.  bend angle induced by IHF is approximately 160° [8980235].
IHF is necessary for  induction of <RP> arginine- and lysine-dependent acid resistance (AR)</RP> via both transcriptional and translational controls of gene expression, as IHF activates expression of a specific set of genes involved in <RP> survival at extremely acidic pH </RP> [24816374].
</SUMMARY>
