<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
AsnC is a transcriptional regulator that activates  expression of asnA, a gene involved in <RP> synsis of asparagine</RP> [2864330, 3909107]. However, when asparagine is present  activation of asnA is turned off. On  or hand, <ACTREG>AsnC is negatively autoregulated, but  presence of asparagine does not affect this regulation</ACTREG> [2864330].
AsnC <EVF>belongs to  AsnC family of regulatory proteins</EVF> whose members are widely distributed in archaea and bacteria [11523004]. It has been postulated that AsnC is very ascient; it appears that it was present before  divergence of archea and bacteria [11523004].<DOM> This protein has a DNA-binding domain with a helix-turn-helix motif in  N terminus and an effector-binding C-terminal domain [16528101].</DOM>
A crystal structure of AsnC complexed with  ligand l-asparagine has been solved at 2.4-Å resolution.  crystal structure shows an octamer with l-asparagine bound in a cleft at  interface between dimers; however,  octamer is formed in an l-asparagine-independent manner [16528101].  octamer is composed of four dimers, each of which appears to <SSA>recognize and bind an <SSZ><SSM>inverted repeat DNA sequence</SSM> of 5 bp separated by 3 bp</SSZ> that are usually T or A base pairs</SSA>. re are four AsnC sites in  divergent regulatory regions of asnA and asnC, and y are separated by 18 bp. 
replication origin, oriC, is located between  mioC and gidA genes, and <TUL> asnC gene is immediately upstream of mioC in  genome</TUL> [2864330].  transcription of asnC sometimes traverses  origin of replication and continues into gidA, possibly explaining  effect on gidA expression [2836709, 2464126, 2854096]. Sometimes  transcription of asnC ends at a terminator located downstream of this gene or by  DnaA protein that binds to a DnaA box blocking  transcribing RNA polymerase [2464126, 2854096].
<TUCREG>Expression of asnC is regulated by nitrogen availability; under nitrogen-limiting conditions, Nac represses asnC</TUCREG> [11814655].
Review: [16438681].
</SUMMARY>