<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
CytR,  Cytidine Regulator,  is a transcription factor required for <RP>transport and utilization of ribonucleosides and deoxyribonucleosides</RP> [7715459, 8596434, 8022285, 1715855, 9466254, 9767576, 14499937].
 repressor CytR and  activator CRP, two dimeric proteins, interact to form a complex repressor nucleoprotein in  intergenic region. When only CRP is bound to this promoter, it functions as an activator, and n, <ACTCONDP>when CytR binds to DNA and to CRP,  activation is repressed because CytR masks an activating region of CRP that orwise would contact  RNA polymerase to activate transcription</ACTCONDP>  [8736525, 10766824, 9086266, 10320573, 10766824, 8764393, 8816767].
 CytR protein cannot act alone; <ACTCONDP> synergistic DNA binding is increased by direct interaction with CRP</ACTCONDP> [1962841, 2170326, 1649947]. However, footprinting analyses showed that  dimers of CytR are flanked or  sandwiched  by two dimers of CRP [1655726, 10766824, 10347150, 8969182]. At times CytR also repositions CRP to alternative DNA-binding sites that are not functional for activation [8736525]. 
Gavigan et al. (1999) and Perini et al. (1996) showed that CytR binds in tandem in  regulated intergenic region [10347150, 8969182]. On  or hand, in 1997, Pedersen and Valentin-Hanses showed that <SSA>CytR binds to <SSM>octamer repeats</SSM>, GTTGCATT in eir  direct or inverted orientation and preferably separated by 2 or 3 bp</SSA> [9155036, 15313602, 9466254]. For this reason  length of  CytR DNA-binding site is variable.
Gene induction occurs when  physiological inducer, cytidine, binds to  CytR regulator and when cellular cAMP levels are high. <ACTCONDN>CytR senses and binds <ACTEFFE>cytidine</ACTEFFE>, and when this happens  cooperativity of CytR and CRP is interrupted and  expression of genes is induced</ACTCONDN> [1655726, 1715855].
CytR <EVF>belongs to  GalR/LacI family of transcriptional regulators</EVF> [1639817]. <DOM>Like  or members of this family, it has an N-terminal domain that contains a helix-turn-helix (HTH) motif for DNA binding and a C-terminal domain for dimerization, inducer binding [1639817] and protein contact with CRP [9215632]. Between se two domains, CytR has a disordered sequence that provides  HTH motif with freedom of movement [9155036, 9466254], which would allow this protein to interact with octameric half DNA-binding sites that could be arranged as inverted or  direct repeats and with different lengths of spacer regions [9466254, 9155036]. This interdomain linker is protected from proteolytic digestion in  presence of CRP [15313602].</DOM>
Based on nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy,  structure of  CytR DNA-binding domain (DBD) bound to  udp half-site and characterization of  free state were obtained [21688840].
<TUR> cytR gene is autorepressed and is <TUCREG>activated by CRP</TUCREG></TUR> [2162467, 1328649].
Review: [8736525, 10066473].
</SUMMARY>