<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
transcription factor IclR, for  Isocitrate lyase Regulator,  <TUR><ACTREG>is negatively autoregulated</ACTREG></TUR> [8550439] and it regulates  expression of  <RP>glyoxylate bypass</RP> operon  [18942160, 8626344, 1995429, 2512996, 7033207, 2001680]. Transcription of this operon is induced when E. coli is grown during acetate accumulation in  exponential phase. <ACTEFFE>Glyoxylate and pyruvate have been identified as effectors</ACTEFFE> of IclR and show antagonistic effects. While <ACTCONDN>glyoxylate favors  inactive dimeric state of IclR</ACTCONDN>, <ACTCONDP>pyruvate increases  binding of IclR to  aceBp promoter</ACTCONDP> by stabilizing  <ACTCONF>active tetrameric form of  protein</ACTCONF> [17426033].
On or hand,  genes of  aceBAK operon are expressed to varied degrees due to two facts: first, y are differentially regulated at  translational level, and second, re is a putative premature transcriptional termination in  region preceding  aceK gene [16415587]. 

IclR represses aceBAK transcription through two mechanisms [12492863] (1) binding to  proximal site, overlapping  -35 promoter box, and preventing RNA polymerase binding [8682810, 1447784, 2001680] and (2) binding to  distal site after  RNA polymerase has bound to  promoter and formed  open complex, avoiding  polymerase escape of  promoter through its interaction with  α-subunits. Perhaps  IclR binding at both sites forms an intermolecular bridge that leads to a DNA loop structure and thus enhances  aceBAK  repression [12492863].
This regulator <EVF>belongs to  IclR family of repressors</EVF>. <DOM>IclR is composed of two domains:  amino-terminal domain, which contains  DNA-binding region, and  carboxy-terminal domain, which is responsible for inducer binding [1447784, 2185227, 17426033, 8844850, 1995431].</DOM>
 crystal structure of  C-terminal domain of IclR (2.3Å) has been solved  [17426033].
An iclR mutation affects  carbon flow in  metabolism [15543598, 15885621].
Review: [22382436].
</SUMMARY>