<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
CadC is a metal-sensitive transcriptional activator that regulates  expression of genes involved in <RP>cadaverine synsis and excretion</RP> <ACTCONDP>under low external pH and high concentrations of lysine</ACTCONDP> [1370290, 8195083, 16491024].
Two binding sites for CadC, Cad1 and Cad2, have been determined in  cadBA operon. While Cad1 <SSM>contains an inverted repeat sequence</SSM>, Cad2 lacks eir an inverted repeat or a palindromic sequence. Both binding sites are necessary for cadBA activation. Under aerobic conditions, H-NS represses  cadBA operon. Upon binding to Cad1, CadC releases  bound H-NS molecules, dissolving  H-NS repressor complex and allowing RNA polymerase binding. Transcription of cadBA is finally activated once a molecule of CadC binds to Cad2 [16491024].
CadC is an integral membrane protein that <EVF>belongs to  ToxR-like family of transcriptional activators</EVF>. It features a cytoplasmic DNA-binding N-terminal domain, a transmembrane domain, and a periplasmic C-terminal domain [16491024].
<ACTREG><ACTCONDN>In  absence of lysine, LysP regulates CadC negatively</ACTCONDN> [8195083]. This inhibition is through intramembrane and perisplasmic contacts under noninducing conditions. Based on site-directed mutagenesis</ACTREG>, <DOM>Asp275 and Asp278 in LysP and Arg265 and Arg268 in CadC were identified as residues for  stimulus-dependent interaction between m [24056175].</DOM>
<ACTEFFE>LysP and CadC interact most strongly at pH7.6 and at lysine concentrations of 1 µM or less</ACTEFFE>, that is, under non-Cad-inducing conditions. This interaction is attenuated under Cad-inducing conditions (low pH, increased lysine levels). <ACTREG> LysP-CadC interaction is mediated via trans-membrane and periplasmic contacts [24056175]</ACTREG>. Oligomerization of LysP is induced at low pH [24056175]. LysP is a trigger transporter [19708919], i.e., a protein that combines regulation and transport functions within  one polypeptide.
At neutral cytoplasmic pH,  <DOM>a disulfide bond is formed in  periplasmic domain of CadC to inactivate it.</DOM> At low pH, formation  of  disulfide bond is prevented, which in turn converts CadC into an active state, but only if lysine is present to inactivate to LysP,  negative regulator  of CadC [21486484].
</SUMMARY>