<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Rob is a transcriptional dual regulator. <EVPIT>Its N-terminal domain shares 49% identity with MarA and SoxS</EVPIT> [8383113]. se proteins activate a common set of about 50 target genes [10852879, 12067348, 14712652, 11395452]  marA/soxS/rob regulon, involved <RP>in antibiotic resistance [8636021, 15853893, 7896685] superoxide resistance [8626315, 1400156, 1317841] and tolerance to organic solvents [9324261, 9783171]and heavy metals [7793951]</RP>.  activity of each protein is induced by different signals: <ACTCONDP> activity of Rob is increased with dipyridyl, bile salts, or decanoate</ACTCONDP> [11844771, 12791142] and  activities of MarA and SoxS are increased by  aromatic weak acid salicylate [11395452]and oxidative stress [8955629] respectively. Cross talk between  mar and rob systems plays an important role in  response to salicylate [22753060]. 
Many genes are regulated by all three proteins; however, some genes are regulated by only one of m.  differential regulation of se genes might be caused by  degeneracy of ir DNA-binding sites [14594836]. 
Rob, MarA, and SoxS bind as monomers to  same DNA site, <TURO>a <SSA>degenerate <SSZ>20-bp sequence</SSZ></SSA> known as  Mar-Sox-Rob box</TURO>, which has to be in a specific orientation and distance relative to   -35 and  -10 boxes of  promoter [10564485, 10564484]. In class I promoters,  activators bind upstream of   -35 box and are generally oriented in  backward direction, while in class II promoters  proteins overlap   -35 promoter hexamer and generally are oriented in  forward direction [10564485, 10564484, 22465792]. As a subset of  class I promoters,  Mar-Sox-Rob box is separated by ~30 bp from   -10 hexamer but can be functional in eir orientation [10564485, 10564484].
<SSA> Mar-Sox-Rob box contains an  invariant A  at position 1, two recognition elements,  RE1 at position 4-7 and RE2 at position 15-18, and a 7-bp A/T-rich spacer separating se elements</SSA> [10802742, 11724537, 11401718]. re are more than 10,000 such binding sites per genome [11866462]. However,  majority of se sites are not functional because y are not in  proper orientation or distance relative to  promoter [11985714]. It was proposed that se proteins bind to ir target sites by a mechanism named  DNA scanning  or  prerecruitment.  In prerecruitment,  protein first binds to RNA polymerase in solution, and  binary complex n scans  DNA to find its binding sites [11985714, 11866462]. 
<DOM>Rob consists of two domains and belongs to  AraC/XylS family [9409145].  N-terminal domain is  DNA-binding domain and is homologous to MarA and SoxS and  C-terminal domain of AraC. It carries two helix-turn-helix (HTH) motifs for DNA binding. One of m, located in  N-terminal region, interacts with  element RE1 of  Mar-Sox-Rob box, and  HTH located in  C-terminal region interacts with RE2 [12217688, 9724717, 11724537]. In  case of Rob, it appears that only one of  two HTH motifs makes base-specific contacts with DNA [10802742].</DOM>  crystal structures of Rob [10802742] and MarA [9724717] in complex with DNA and  solution structure of  DNA-binding domain of AraC [19422057]have been solved.
 C-terminal domain of Rob is similar to a portion of  enzyme GalT [10802742]. It regulates  activity of Rob by a  sequestration-disposal  mechanism, that is, it mediates  sequestration of Rob into intracellular foci. Sequestered Rob is inactive. <ACTCONF>Upon addition of  inducer, Rob is released in its active form</ACTCONF> [19289129].  C-terminal domain blocks in addition proteolytic degradation by Lon protease [19289129].
rob appears to be transcribed abundantly at 5,000-10,000 molecules per cell [8449900, 10515926] throughout  growth cycle. <TUCREG>rob expression is enhanced at  stationary phase and under glucose and phosphate starvation</TUCREG>, and <TUR>it was suggested that expression of rob is σS dependent</TUR> [7476863]. 
Reviews: [10498949, 8955629, 12027588].
</SUMMARY>