<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
FlhD and FlhC proteins are transcriptional factors and can form homodimers independently (FlhD2 and FlhC2)  [7961507] and  assembly of se homodimers results in  formation of heterotetramers (FlhD2C2)  [7961507, 12144778, 15941987].  complex transcription factor FlhD2C2 is  principal regulator of bacterial flagellum biogenesis and swarming migration  [12144778, 15941987]. This heterotetrameric regulator activates class II genes involved in <RP> flagellar basal body [12144778, 15941987, 7961507, 10650844]  proteins of  export machinery,  flagellar σ subunit (FliA), and its anti-σ factor, FlgM</RP> [12144778, 15941987, 15516564]. Currently, no inducer for this regulator has been reported in  literature. A microarray analysis showed that  master regulator, FlhD2C2, regulates several nonflagellar genes,  but  direct effect has not been determined. 
<TUL>FlhD and FlhC are part of  unusual flhDC operon</TUL> that encodes two transcriptional regulators [7961507, 2832369]. <TUR> expression of  flhDC master operon is multirregulated by several systems including those that respond to high osmolarity [7642497] catabolic repression [10601207] quorum sensing [11929534] synsis of type 1 fimbriae [12123461]  histone-like nucleoid protein [8071234, 10601207] heat shock, etc.</TUR>
 flagellar regulator activates transcription of class II genes by overlapping  -35 box of  promoters [15941987, 12144778, 7961507]. <SSA> binding targets for FlhD2C2 consist of <SSM>two repeat sequences</SSM> that possess conserved motifs; each heterodimer (FlhDC) binds  to one of se conserved sequences, which are separated by a 10- to 11-bp spacer</SSA> [15941987, 12144778]. 
 flagellar regulator is conformed by two FlhD subunits and two FlhC subunits, as a heterotetramer [16337229] while <DOM>FlhD is constituted by two domains:  N-terminal domain is responsible for dimerization and  C terminal is a highly flexible domain contain  DNA-binding (helix-turn-helix motif) region [16337229, 11169099]. FlhC is constituted by two domains; arrangement of  domains is unique in  FlhC family [16337229].</DOM>  crystal structure of FlhDC has been solved to 3 Å resolution [16337229].
 </SUMMARY>