<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
genes regulated by NanR,  N-acetyl-neuraminic acid regulator,  are involved in <RP>N-acetyl-neuraminic acid (or sialic acid) transport and metabolism [12897000] and in OFF/ON  switching of type 1 fimbriation</RP>. N-acetylneuraminate (Neu5Ac), which is  most common sialic acid, induces  catabolism of sialic acids operons by directly inactivating NanR [15534208] converting  predominantly dimeric form of  repressor to an inactive monomer [23935044].
NanR is a <EVF>member of  FadR/GntR family</EVF>. <DOM>Members of this family have two domains, an N-terminal domain with a helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motif and a C-terminal domain with dimerization and effector-binding motifs.</DOM> Three-dimensional models of  <EVPIDT>N terminus of FadR and NanR show topological similarities and a ~26% sequence identity between m</EVPIDT> [12897000].
NanR regulates transcription when <SSA>it binds to <SSZ>a region of ~30 bp</SSZ> that contains <SSM>three conserved motifs in tandem</SSM></SSA>. However, this protein can be displaced from this region by N-acetyl-neuraminic acid. Although it has been shown that NanR can form homodimers in solution, <ACTCONF>its DNA-binding stoichiometry is unknown</ACTCONF>. When this protein is repressing transcription, it overlaps  whole promoter region [12897000, 15534208].  Nan box shows affinity to a set of conserved operators with two or three exact, or nearly exact, repeats of  hexanucleotide sequence GGTATA [23935044].
 region of <SSZ>30 bp that NanR binds to</SSZ> is close to a Dam methylation site (GATC) [18054045, 15534208] that appears to be necessary for induction of some genes of  NanR regulon [12139615]. Methylation in se sites is prevented by NanR binding [18054045, 15534208].
Kalivoda et. al. (2013) have suggested that  term sialoregulon be given to genes that are directly regulated by NanR and  term sialostimulon be used for genes affected by  by-products of sialic acid metabolism [23935044].
 crystal structure of  native NanR has been solved [23935044].
 </SUMMARY>