<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
transcription factor IscR, for  Iron-sulfur cluster Regulator,  <ACTREG>is negatively autoregulated</ACTREG>, and it contains an iron-sulfur cluster that could act as a sensor of iron-sulfur cluster assembly [11742080, 16677314]. This protein regulates  expression of  operons that encode components of <RP>a secondary pathway of iron-sulfur cluster assembly, iron-sulfur proteins, anaerobic respiration enzymes, and biofilm formation</RP> [11432781, 11742080, 16677314, 18849427, 16824106, 19074392].
IscR is a <EVF>member of  Rrf2 family</EVF> [19361432] and <DOM>carries a predicted N-terminal helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motif and three conserved cysteines in its C terminus. IscR is a dimer in solution [19361432] and it contains  [2Fe-2S]1+ cluster when purified under anaerobic conditions [11742080]. This [2Fe-2S]1+ cluster has an unusual (Cys)3(His)1 ligand scheme and is essential for cluster ligation [22583201].</DOM> Some proteins, such as SufB, IscU, EprA, and IscA, are involved in  assembly and transfer of  [2Fe-2S] cluster to IscR [23320508]. Two types of DNA-binding sites have been described for IscR: type 1 and type 2. <SSA>Both sites resemble <SSZ>25-bp</SSZ> <SSM>imperfect palindromes</SSM> but differ in ir sequence</SSA> [16677314, 19361432]. <ACTCONF>IscR requires  iron-sulfur cluster for its activity when bound to type 1 sites</ACTCONF>. <ACTEFFE> binding of  [2Fe-2S]1+ cluster</ACTEFFE> allows IscR to induce a conformational change, mainly around  residue Glu43, that modifies its DNA-binding affinity. This modification enables IscR to bind to type 1 DNA-binding sites  [23644595].
 PiscR contains two type 1 sites [16677314]. refore, under conditions when Fe-S cluster assembly becomes rate limiting, levels of [2Fe-2S]-containing IscR may decrease due to a lower rate of its synsis, thus relieving repression of  iscRSUA operon for  biogenesis of  iron-sulfur cluster [11742080, 11752417, 23075318]. In contrast, for  regulation of promoters containing type 2 sites, such as PsufA,  [2Fe-2S] cluster of IscR is dispensable [16824106, 18849427].
IscR binds cooperatively to DNA, and four protomers bind to one palindromic site [19361432].
</SUMMARY>