<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
SutR (formely YdcN) regulates a set of genes involved in <RP> utilization of sulfur</RP> [25406449]. <DOM>SutR is a small transcription factor with a helix-turn-helix (HTH) motif</DOM> and <EVF>belongs to  Cro-C1-type superfamily</EVF> [20491932]. Based on genomic SELEX screen analysis, it was identified as a highly probable regulator for 12-16 operons involved in various steps of sulfur utilization, playing an important role in  coordination of expression of  genes involved in this metabolic pathway [25406449]. 
Genes identified by SELEX analysis include  following: paoC, xseB, thiI, ydcO, sutR, ynfG, ydiY, pfkB, fliZ, ypfN, yfgM, yfiC, tdcF, cysE, and yjcS.  Four peaks were located in type A spacers of divergent transcription units (TUs), and eight peaks were identified within type B spacers upstream of one TU but downstream of  preceding TUs [25406449].
A <SSA><SSM>direct repeat</SSM> GCGT motif</SSA> of  SutR box was found in  yfiC, ydcO, and sutR genes, which are associated with group A spacers, and  <SSM>palindromic sequence</SSM> of GCGT(Nn)ACGC was identified for yfiC, thiI, ydcO, and sutR genes [25406449]. On  or hand, in  group B spacers,  direct repeat GCGT was identified upstream of  tdcF, yfgM, and ynfG genes while  palindromic GCGT(Nn)ACGC sequence was found in  fliZ gene [25406449]. 
Genes identified by microarray analysis include several for repression by SutR, sutR, ydcO, pfkB, fliZ, and cysE, while activation of SutR was identified only for ypfN [25406449].
 following genes were identified via chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) in vivo: sutR, cysE, and fliZ [25406449].
 highest level of SutR binding was found in  spacer in  ydcO-sutR region. Based on DNA footprinting assay results, two regions for SutR were identified  in  ydcO-sutR spacer sequence. One of m that was identified,  strongest SutR-binding site, is called site 1, and it represses ydcO and activates sutR expression; it is a direct repeat, GCGT, separated by 4 bp. On  or hand, site 2 overlaps  -35 and -10 boxes of  sutRp promoter [25406449].
SutR, for regulator of sulfur utilization [25406449].
</SUMMARY>