<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
OxyR,  oxidative stress regulator,  is  transcriptional dual regulator for  expression of antioxidant genes <ACTCONDP>in response to oxidative stress, in particular, elevated levels of hydrogen peroxide</ACTCONDP>.  OxyR regulon includes genes involved in <RP>peroxide metabolism, redox balance, and peroxide protection by, for example, manganese uptake [2256675, 11443091, 12100544, 19400769]. Moreover, OxyR activates  synsis of  small, noncoding oxyS RNA</RP>. This allows OxyR to regulate as many as 40 additional gene products indirectly by affecting mRNA stability or translation efficiency [9230301]. <TUCREG><ACTREG>OxyR acts as a repressor for its own synsis in <ACTCONF>both  oxidized and reduced forms</ACTCONF></ACTREG></TUCREG> [2471187, 1864839]. In addition, <TUCREG>expression of oxyR is positively regulated by cAMP-activated Crp protein during exponential growth and negatively regulated by RpoS when cells enter stationary phase</TUCREG> [9324269]. Based on microarray assays, a new function as regulator of <RP>S-nitrosylation</RP> (a nitrosative stress regulon) under anaerobic conditions has been determined for OxyR [22539721] and it is distinct from  OxyR regulon activated by oxidative stress [22539721].
OxyR consists of 305 amino acid residues and is a member of  LysR family of bacterial transcription factors [2471187, 2511419]. It is a tetramer in solution [7868603]. <DOM>OxyR consists of two domains,  N-terminal domain, carrying a helix-turn-helix motif, and  C-terminal regulatory domain. A flexible linker connects both domains.  C-terminal domain contains  determinants for oligomerization and two redox-active cysteines, Cys199 and Cys208 [7868603, 15543158, 12595552]. OxyR functions as a reversible cellular redox switch. <ACTCONDP>In  presence of 100 nM H2O2, activation occurs by  formation of an intramolecular disulfide bond between Cys199 and Cys208</ACTCONDP> [2183352, 15543158].</DOM> Inactivation involves reduction of  disulfide bond by glutaredoxin 1 and glutathione [9497290]. Oxidation is significantly faster than reduction, allowing for transient activation in a reducing environment [10339558]. <ACTCONDP>OxyR is also activated under nitrosative stress</ACTCONDP>; this reaction involves S-nitrosylation of OxyR [8797819].  crystal structures of  regulatory domain of OxyR in both its reduced and oxidized forms have been solved. Comparison of both structures reveals that oxidation is accompanied by a significant structural change in  regulatory domain [11301006].
In systematic studies of oligomerization, it was shown that some members of  LysR family, like OxyR, interact with or members of  family to form heterodimers, but  physiological significance of this is unknown [21187915]. OxyR can bind as a pair of dimers bending to  DNA [12706716, 22692422]. 
OxyR <SSA>recognizes a motif comprised of ATAGnt elements spaced at 10-bp intervals</SSA> [8087856].  binding to DNA differs significantly for  oxidized and reduced forms [8087856]. Reduced OxyR <SSA>binds DNA at two pairs of major grooves separated by one helical turn, while oxidized OxyR occupies four consecutive major grooves</SSA>. When bound to DNA, oxidized OxyR stimulates transcription by interacting with  C-terminal domain of  α-subunit of RNA polymerase [7592462].
Review: [22381957].
</SUMMARY>