<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
Lactose inhibitor, LacI, is a DNA-binding transcription factor that represses transcription of  operon involved in <RP>transport and catabolism of lactose</RP> [2166165, 8568874, 15950160]. In  absence of allolactose, LacI represses  lac operon by preventing open promoter complex formation for transcription [2166165, 21829165]. In this repression system, LacI binds to two operators, and formation of  repressor loop is critical [8984648, 8984647, 14725772, 2166165]. 
<SSA>This repressor binds in tandem to <SSM>inverted repeat sequences</SSM> that are <SSZ>21 nucleotides long</SSZ> and possess conserved motifs</SSA> [2166165, 8984648, 8984647]. <ACTREG>LacI is negatively autoregulated when it binds to two DNA-binding sites, one located downstream of  lacI gene and  or one located in  coding sequence for  C terminus of LacI</ACTREG>.  protein when bound to se sites forms a loop that inhibits  transcription elongation, thus producing truncated proteins that are tagged for degradation by  small peptide SsrA [10899129, 23658223]. <ACTCONDN>Induction occurs when  physiological inducer, allolactose, binds to  lac repressor, preventing it from binding to  operator</ACTCONDN> [2166165, 15950160]. <ACTCONDN>Nonphysiological analogs, such as thiogalactosides, can function as inducers too</ACTCONDN>. 
A single mutation, W220F, in  inducer-binding site of  LacI repressor reduces leakiness [23807194].  LacI protein <EVF>belongs to  GalR/LacI family</EVF> and as a member of this family of transcriptional regulators, <DOM>LacI contains three domains: a helix-turn-helix motif located in  N terminus,  central domain that binds to LacI sugar ligands, and  C terminal, which comprises  tetramerization domain [15950160].  crystal structure of  LacI binding site for allosteric effectors has been resolved [17543986]. 
 importance of  N125 and D149 residues of  N terminal in  recognition of  sugar effector binding site has been determined [17543986, 21928765].</DOM> Based on a computational rod model of  DNA-LacI complex,  looping of both linear DNA and supercoiled DNA minicircles over a broad range of DNA interoperator lengths was analyzed.  analysis showed that  most stable loops for linear DNA occur when LacI adopts  extended conformation [21806940]. 
On  or hand, in an in vivo single-molecule assay,  sliding process for  LacI TF was determined. LacI slides 45 +/- 10 bp on chromosomal DNA, and this can be obstructed by or DNA-bound proteins near  operator. LacI slides over its natural lacO1 operator several times before binding ARRAY(0x15c0af0), suggesting a trade-off between a rapid search on nonspecific sequences and fast binding at  specific sequence [22723426].
</SUMMARY>