<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
transcriptional activator FUR, for  Ferric Uptake Regulation,  is capable of controlling its own synsis [3079747, 17921503, 10411720, 2836193] and controls  transcription of genes involved in <RP>iron homeostasis [11282473, 11101675, 12475930, 9575233, 17921503, 8407793, 10411720, 2644221, 15101990, 2162465, 3294800] and a minor sigma factor that initiates transcription of ferric citrate transport genes in response to  presence of periplasmic iron(III) dicitrate [17921503, 12860393, 9575233]. This regulator also participates in  regulation of transcription of many or genes involved in different cellular functions, including  following: flagellum chemotaxis [8107138] methionine biosynsis [8107138] acid and oxidative stresses [8412671, 11101675] metal ion stress [11466284, 17120142, 12480884] resistance to cobalt and nickel [17129142]  tricarboxylic acid cycle [9418241, 15659676] glycolysis and gluconeogenesis [11101675] respiration [8107138, 9418241, 15659676] porins [15659676] purine metabolism [8107138] 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate biosynsis [2139473] and phage DNA packaging [11101675]. Based on transcriptome analysis, expression levels of a set of genes regulated by Fur change substantially in response to antibiotic treatment  [25063442]. Iron homeostasis influences  evolution of ciprofloxacin resistance</RP> [25063442].
FUR is a transcriptional repressor but also can be an activator;  positive regulation of this regulator  is mediated by  indirect effect of RhyB, which is an antisense small RNA [17216355, 12975324, 16982641, 16199566, 11917098, 14617150].
FUR is a sensor  of   concentration of intracellular iron, and  <ACTCONDP>genetic repression occurs when  physiological inducer, <ACTEFFE>iron (Fe2+)</ACTEFFE>, binds to FUR</ACTCONDP>. This cofactor is required for DNA binding [16216078, 17216355]. FUR also is considered a  metalloregulatory protein and can sense different  divalent metal ions, such as Zn(II), Cu(II), Cd(II), Co(II), and Mn(II) [3294800, 10350474, 17216355, 11895294, 16216078, 16690618, 19023664]. Transcriptomic and statistical modeling analyses with Zn concentration shifts showed a transient change in  activity of  iron regulator Fur and of  oxidative stress regulator SoxS; se findings suggest a competitive binding mechanism for  physiology of Zn and Fe uptake [22016571]. On  or hand, D'Autr%e';aux et al. showed that nitric oxide, a radical that is potentially toxic, inhibits   DNA binding of this repressor [16417522, 12475930].
<ACTCONDP>In  presence of iron, FUR binds in tandem to possible <SSA><SSM>inverted repeat sequences</SSM> in  intergenic region</SSA></ACTCONDP> to repress transcription by overlapping  -35 box of  regulated promoter.  FUR-binding sites were previously represented as regions of 19 bp, which were determined by footprinting of several promoter sequences [3294800, 2644221, 8107138, 2015825]. Different aligments and computational analysis of se sequences showed different overlapping 15-bp sequences: TGATAATnATTATCA, consisting of two inverted repeats of 7 bp separated by 1 bp [12374814, 17921503]. Experimental support for this consensus sequence was obtained from footprinting, site-directed mutagenesis experiments, analysis of  affinity and stoichiometry of DNA binding, gel retardation assays, etc. [12374814, 12644489]. Currently re are different interpretations and models to explain how FUR could overlap inverted repeats in tandem [12374814, 17921503, 12644489, 16443380].
</SUMMARY>