<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
CitB/DpiA is a dual transcriptional regulator involved in <RP>anaerobic citrate catabolism. <ACTCONDP>In  presence of citrate and under anaerobic conditions it activates genes for citrate fermentation</ACTCONDP>,  citCDEFXGT operon, <TUL> citAB operon</TUL>, and mdh, as well as  exuTR operon for dissimilation of hexuronate [18997424]. 
Due to  ability of CitB/DpiA to bind to A/T-rich sequences, multiple or roles have been assigned to CitB. When overexpressed in E. coli, it destabilizes plasmid inheritance, represses transcription of appY, encoding a regulator of anaerobic metabolism, and induces  SOS response by competing with DnaA and DnaB in binding to <SSA>A/T-rich sequences</SSA> at  replication origin [9701802, 14526013]. Moreover, inactivation of penicillin-binding protein 3, FtsI, eir chemically or genetically, induces SOS</RP> in E. coli. This induction requires dpiBA [15308764]. 
CitB/DpiA <EVF>belongs to  two-component system DpiB/DpiA, or CitBA</EVF>. <TUL> operon containing both genes, citB (dpiA), encoding  response regulator, and citA (dpiB)</TUL>, encoding  sensor kinase, is transcribed divergently to  citCDEFXGT operon. CitA (DpiB) binds citrate with its periplasmic domain [11889485]and senses reduced conditions using a single Cys residue in vitro [19202292].  cytoplasmic domain is involved in autophosphorylation and phosphotransfer to CitB (DpiA) [19202292]. refore, it has been suggested that  main role of DpiA/CitB is regulation of citrate fermentation [11889485].
CitB/DpiA <EVPIT>shows 47% similarity to  CitB protein from K. pneumoniae</EVPIT>, which also controls  citrate fermentation process [9701802]. Like CitB from K. pneumoniae, <DOM>CitB/DpiA from E. coli contains a helix-turn-helix DNA-binding motif in  C-terminal domain and three well-conserved residues, two aspartates (positions 13 and 57) and one lysine (position 107), in  N-terminal domain</DOM> [9701802]. CitB/DpiA binds to <SSA>sequences with a very high A + T content</SSA> [9223636, 19202292].
Dpi: destabilizes plasmid inheritance.
</SUMMARY>
