<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
H-NS protein, for  Histone-like nucleoid structuring protein,  is a nucleoid-associated multifunctional protein that is capable of condensing [10982869] and supercoiling DNA [16384714, 15853876, 11282470, 8306968]. It is a global transcriptional silencer of genes with high AT content [15100692, 18387844] regulates 5% of all Escherichia coli genes [11298273] and plays a key role in global chromosome organization in bacteria [21903814]. This protein acts as a pleiotropic transcriptional factor with a strong preference for horizontally acquired genes among  250 loci to which it binds [2126011, 17046956]. H-NS functions almost exclusively as a transcriptional repressor, although re is no clear evidence that this regulator is an activator. Currently, <ACTEFFE>no inducer for this regulator has been reported in  literature</ACTEFFE>, although Reush et al. proposed that this regulator can form a complex with a short chain of polyhydroxybutyrate [12220682]. Additional genes might be identified by high-throughput analysis [19151137].
H-NS plays an important role in  regulation of many genes in response to environmental changes and adaptation to stress; refore, <TUR>it is  capable of controlling its own synsis</TUR> [7934818, 8830277]. It also regulates transcription of many or genes that  participate in a variety of cellular functions, including genes involved in  following processes or responses: <RP>biogenesis of flagella [8071234, 10601207, 11872702] transcription control of  type I fimbria structural genes [9922259, 9352908, 9595659, 7510658, 9749677] acid resistance  [16204188]  functional glutamic acid-dependent system [10383761] osmotically inducible genes [9663683]  glutamate decarboxylase-dependent acid resistance system [15795232, 12446650, 11976288, 11298273] osmotic control [8120010, 11673423]  type II secretion pathway [11118204] carbon sources [2160266] genes involved in  RNA component of  small subunit (30S subunit) [9632265, 15686546]  and proteases [16143461] among ors. It has also been shown to be involved in survival during stationary phase</RP>, conferring to  bacteria a growth advantage during stationary phase (GASP) [22843842].
H-NS is capable of inducing severe bends in  DNA, interacting with a large number of DNA regions that contain a planar curvature [2126011, 1745240, 14627810]. It has been suggested that H-NS <SSA>binds strongly to sites carrying a <SSZ>10-bp AT-rich consensus sequence</SSZ></SSA>, which functions as a nucleation site for  formation of a repressive higher-order nucleoprotein complex [17881364, 19740756]. H-NS binds to intergenic regions as well as regions within genes, but not all genes that bind H-NS are affected by this protein, a fact that is in agreement with  primary role assigned to HN-S in maintenance of nucleoid structure. Currently, re are different models for  formation of DNA-H-NS-DNA bridges which show that this protein binds in tandem to sequences in  genome, forming multimers [15853876, 17191074, 16879983].
As expected for a gene involved in  modulation of many cellular processes,  expression of hns is regulated by several systems and at different levels. At  transcription level, <TUR>hns is autoregulated</TUR>, and it is controlled by different transcription factors. <TUCREG>hns is induced by high hydrostatic pressure [8226663] and DNA synsis</TUCREG> [8596450]. At  posttranscriptional level, it is subject to regulation by  sRNAs Hfq and DsrA [11115103, 12554874, 15814430, 15147838, 12753181].
It is a DNA-binding protein with similarity to StpA [7961433, 1480493]and se two proteins can have similar functions [10515926, 10947847]. It has an approximately fivefold-lower affinity for DNA than StpA and has a major preference for curved DNA [11278075].  StpA appears to be a backup for Hns in  regulation of a set of nonessential and recently acquired genes [23661089].
Expression of stpA from a plasmid can complement an hns mutant phenotype and StpA is able to repress and activate a subset of H-NS-regulated genes, but  specific mechanisms remain to be determined [7961433, 11278075, 8890170, 8635467, 19151137, 8890170]. A dominant negative form of StpA can disrupt H-NS activity and vice versa, and H-NS can interact with StpA at two distinct domains to form heterodimers in vitro; also, re is evidence that se proteins can form homodimers [11244076, 8755860, 10203842, 8755860]. For this reason, <ACTREG>in  absence of H-NS  StpA protein is rapidly degraded in a Lon protease-dependent manner</ACTREG> [11244076, 10485902] protection from proteolytic degradation appears to be mediated by a direct interaction between StpA and H-NS [11244076]. On  or hand H-NS also may form heterotrimeric complexes with Hha and YdgT [17116239, 15458420]. It was proposed that Hha enhances  oligomerization of Hns/StpA which is necessary to form DNA-protein filaments to repress transcription [23543115, 23601147].  high-resolution structure based on solid-state NMR spectra from full-length H-NS has been determined [23601147]. 
H-NS is a small protein and it is an abundant nucleic acid protein in  genome, with about 20,000 copies per cell.<DOM> This regulator <EVF>belongs to  histone-like family of transcriptional regulators</EVF> and  structure of  protein consists of two structured domains which are separated by a flexible linker [15100692].  N-terminal domain is required for oligomerization and it  is involved in protein-protein interactions, while  purified C-terminal domain is involved in DNA binding [15100692, 10203842, 8755860, 15063845, 19740756].  cooperative binding of H-NS to DNA is related to protein-protein interactions [24275506].
H-NS forms two compact clusters associated with each copy of  chromosome. se clusters are located near  one-quarter and three-quarter positions along  long axis of  cell [21903814]. In cells with three clusters,  additional cluster tends to appear in  middle [21903814].  two cluster formations are induced by  N-terminal domain-driven oligomerization of  protein [21903814].</DOM> H-NS sequesters  regulated genes and operons into se clusters and juxtaposed numerous DNA segments broadly distributed throughout  chromosome [21903814]. Wang et al. (2011) reported that H-NS clusters could thus serve as anchoring points for numerous DNA loci distributed throughout  genome, creating DNA loops connecting  anchored loci [21903814]. 
It was found that  promoter islands, which are regions of DNA containing multiple transcription start sites, are recognized and inactivated by HNS. se promoter islands are associated with genes acquired horizontally [23717391].
Based on ChIP-chip and chip-seq analysis, it was proved that Rho-dependent termination abrogates  H-NS-DNA interactions, leading to transcriptional derepression of H-NS-silenced genes [24499790].
Reviews: [16879983, 17191074, 15853876, 9513262, 15100692, 12753181].
</SUMMARY>