<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<SUMMARY xmlns="http://your_namespace"
				xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
				xsi:schemaLocation="http://your_namespace
				../esquema.xsd">
MelR,  melibiose regulator,  is a transcription factor involved in disaccharide melibiose degradation.  It coregulates with CRP, a global transcriptional regulator [11742992, 10760178, 2851497]. se regulators bind cooperatively to activate transcription of  operon involved in <RP>transport and catabolism of melibiose</RP>. <TUCREG>Synsis of this operon is induced when Escherichia coli is grown on melibiose in  absence of glucose</TUCREG>. Gene induction occurs when  physiological inducer, melibiose, binds to  MelR regulator and when cellular cyclic AMP levels are high.
In  presence of melibiose, MelR binds in tandem to repeat sequences in  melR/melAB intergenic region to activate transcription by overlapping  -35 box of  promoter melAp. <SSA> binding targets for MelR consist of <SSZ>18-nucleotide-long repeat sequences</SSZ> that possess conserved motifs</SSA>; each monomer binds to one of se conserved sequences [10760178, 11742992, 10747919]. 
MelR binds to five target sites in  melAp region. MelR binds to  less-conserved site (-42.5) with less strength; this binding occurs only in  presence of melibiose, and it is absolutely required for expression of melAp [10760178]. MelR binding to  distal site (-237.5) has been shown to down-regulate  expression of melRp and melAp [16621812, 10760179]. 
<ACTREG>In  absence of melibiose, MelR is unable to activate melAp, but <TUR>it regulates its own expression by repressing melRp and melAp simultaneously</TUR></ACTREG> [10760178, 11752325, 9409145]. Melibiose triggers MelR-dependent activation of melAp and relieves MelR-dependent repression of melRp [9409145, 11752325]. <TUL> melAB operon is located upstream of melR and in  opposite direction.</TUL>
This regulator <EVF>belongs to  AraC/XylS family of activators</EVF> and occurs as both a monomer and a homodimer. <DOM>It is composed of two domains:  carboxy-terminal domain, which contains  DNA-binding region, and  amino-terminal domain, which is responsible for dimerization and l-arabinose binding [7784205, 2684786, 1445207, 9108148, 12675795]. </DOM>
</SUMMARY>
